<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/note/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 17:30:08 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/note/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Humans</title>
      <link>/note/managing-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 17:30:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/note/managing-humans/</guid>
      <description>Michael Loop has worked as a manager at various companies in silicon valley, and his stories and lessons in Managing Humans are really helpful. Here are some miscellaneous takeaways from my recent reading.
Every Company (Probably) Has Big Problems Turns out I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen prey to the &amp;ldquo;grass is always greener&amp;rdquo; fallacy. I realize that no company is perfect, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always worked at companies that seem to have pretty big problems and I always imagine that there&amp;rsquo;s some company somewhere in Silicon Valley that &amp;mdash; while imperfect &amp;mdash; &amp;ldquo;has it&amp;rsquo;s shit together&amp;rdquo; on the fundamentals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is an Object Graph?</title>
      <link>/note/what-is-an-object-graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 May 2017 16:12:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/note/what-is-an-object-graph/</guid>
      <description>When I hear the word &amp;ldquo;graph,&amp;rdquo; I always think of graphs on a cartesian coordinate system. That&amp;rsquo;s not what we&amp;rsquo;re talking about here. Perhaps the easiest way of introducing graphs is to look at a visual representation of one:
What are we looking at here? We see a set of objects represented by circles. The set is [6, 4, 5, 1, 3, 2].
We also see that a subset of those objects have some relationship to one another, which is represented by the lines.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Object Thinking&#39;s Intro</title>
      <link>/note/object-thinkings-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 May 2017 08:57:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/note/object-thinkings-intro/</guid>
      <description>Object Thinking&amp;rsquo;s introduction begins with talking about the ongoing crisis in software:
 The time: 1968. A software crisis has been declared. Part of the crisis derives from the fact that more software is needed than there are developers to produce it. The other part of the crisis is the abysmal record of development efforts. More than half of the projects initiated are canceled, and less than 20 percent of projects are successfully completed&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>