<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Founder Ethics on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/categories/Founder-Ethics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Founder Ethics on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 04:05:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/categories/Founder-Ethics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;ll Probably Try to Manipulate You</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 04:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</guid>
      <description>I became a hippie when I was a freshman in college. When I say I became a hippie, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean that I wore tie dye t-shirts all the time, smoked a lot of weed, and listened to &amp;ldquo;All you need is love&amp;rdquo; all day. I was a hippie even though I owned zero tie dye t-shirts, wasn&amp;rsquo;t cool enough to get invited to the weed parties, and had never heard that famous Beatles song that more conventional hippies love.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should the Idea Person get Extra Equity?</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 12:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my last post, I have some ideas for a startup, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to start working on them.¹ Unfortunately, doing a startup raises a lot of questions that I, as a former wannabe philosophy professor, haven&amp;rsquo;t really considered. Since its probably not a good idea to dive in to a venture that I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand, it seems like I should spend some time wrestling with what we might call &amp;ldquo;startup questions.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m Glad my Dream Job Didn&#39;t work out</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/22/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 03:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/22/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/</guid>
      <description>For the past 5 years of my life, I&amp;rsquo;ve dreamed of having a job where I would get paid to think about interesting and important ideas and to try to get young people to be so passionate about those ideas that they would want to fight anyone who disagrees with them.
For the past 5 years, I hoped I was going to be a philosophy professor
I say &amp;ldquo;hoped&amp;rdquo; because I&amp;rsquo;ve always realized that philosophy professors have a sweet gig and a scandalous job description.</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
