<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>project management on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/tags/project-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in project management on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 18:25:50 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/project-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exposing Imposter User Stories</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/user-story-suprise/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 18:25:50 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/user-story-suprise/</guid>
      <description>The law of raspberry jam &amp;mdash; the more it spreads, the thinner it gets &amp;mdash; definitely applies to &amp;ldquo;agile software development.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;Agile&amp;rdquo; is ubiquitous and nearly meaningless at the same time. You don&amp;rsquo;t learn much about how a company actually operates from hearing that it&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;agile.&amp;rdquo;
This isn&amp;rsquo;t a new claim, and it shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be controversial. OG agile manifesto signatories and prominent programmers have pointed this out already:
 I was among the seventeen middle-aged white guys who gathered at Snowbird, Utah.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Programming and Forecasting</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/improving-forecasting/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 10:34:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/improving-forecasting/</guid>
      <description>Good programmers are good at forecasting. They can often predict roughly how long it&amp;rsquo;ll take to accomplish a particular programming task. They can also predict when and to what extent a project will see ROI from a particular technical investment.
Unfortunately, this skill isn&amp;rsquo;t guaranteed to develop as we gain more experience programming. In Superforecasters, the authors note that many experienced people are surprisingly bad at making forecasts and that time and experience often don&amp;rsquo;t make us any better.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How to Automate Common Jira Tasks with Go Jira Custom Commands</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/jira-cli-fu/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 20:03:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/jira-cli-fu/</guid>
      <description>in all but small teams I typically recommend separate people for the separate roles [of product managment and project management]. But in every case I believe that developing strong project management skills is a big advantage for product managers – at the least your product will get to market faster, and it could make the difference between getting your product shipped at all.
&amp;ndash;Marty Cagan, &amp;ldquo;Ebay&amp;rsquo;s Secret Weapon&amp;rdquo;
  Every morning, I get the following slack message reminder:</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
