<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Rposts on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/rpost/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Rposts on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Avatar The Last Airbender Language Model and Text Generation</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/avatar-last-airbender-language-model-and-text-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/avatar-last-airbender-language-model-and-text-generation/</guid>
      <description>This week’s TidyTuesday data set is basically the script for all of the Avatar: The Last Airbender episodes. I thought it’d be neat to build a language model from the script and use it to generate new sentences that plausibly sound like they belong in the Avatar universe. In this post, I’ll quickly present some of the sentences generated from the model, and then I’ll dive into how I obtained those results.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Tidy Analysis of Astronauts and Their Missions</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/a-tidy-analysis-of-astronauts-and-their-missions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/a-tidy-analysis-of-astronauts-and-their-missions/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I live in Orlando Florida, which is less than an hour away from Cape Canaveral. As you might imagine, visiting the space center and watching launches is a “thing” we Orlando folks do fairly often.
I’ve also been getting into R and data science recently via Garrett Grolemund and Hadley Wickham’s excellent R for Data Science. To apply the things I’m learning, I thought it’d be fun to analyze this week’s Tidy Tuesday astronauts dataset.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Traffic Fatalities by Vehicle Weight and Size with Tidyverse</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/analyzing-traffic-fatalities-by-vehicle-weight-and-size/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/rpost/analyzing-traffic-fatalities-by-vehicle-weight-and-size/</guid>
      <description>I bought a car recently. I’m cheap and practical and I’m going to be a father soon, so the only things I really cared about were:
 will the car keep my wife and child safe if they’re in an accident will the car keep running reliably how do I get 👆 those two things on the cheap  I’ve also been getting into machine learning and data science recently, so I thought it’d be useful to answer them using some data science tools.</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
