<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophy on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/categories/Philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Philosophy on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 01:44:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/categories/Philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Taylor Swift, Photographers, and &#34;working for nothing&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/06/25/taylor-swift-photographers-and-working-for-nothing/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jun 2015 01:44:15 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/06/25/taylor-swift-photographers-and-working-for-nothing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t already know, here&amp;rsquo;s a quick run down of what&amp;rsquo;s happening with the whole Taylor Swift/Apple/Indie Artists debacle: Last month, Apple released its streaming service and offered a three month trial period to users for free. During the trial period, they weren&amp;rsquo;t planning on paying the artists whose music was streamed by the service. Last week, Taylor Swift published &lt;a href=&#34;http://taylorswift.tumblr.com/post/122071902085/to-apple-love-taylor&#34;&gt;an open letter to Apple&lt;/a&gt; in which she basically claimed that Apple was wronging artists by not paying them for three months. Two days ago, Jason Sheldon produced a contract that he had to sign to photograph one of Swift&amp;rsquo;s older tours, and because the contract allows for his work to be used indefinitely without compensating him for each use, &lt;a href=&#34;http://petapixel.com/2015/06/22/an-open-response-to-taylor-swifts-rant-against-apple/&#34;&gt;he basically calls Swift a hypocrite&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;http://money.cnn.com/2015/06/23/media/taylor-swift-photographer-response/&#34;&gt;Swift&amp;rsquo;s spokesman said that Sheldon is misrepresenting the contract&lt;/a&gt;. A few hours ago, Joel Goodman, another freelance photographer, &lt;a href=&#34;http://consequenceofsound.net/2015/06/newly-leaked-contract-stipulates-taylor-swift-can-destroy-equipment-of-defiant-photographers/&#34;&gt;leaked a contract for the 1989 tour that contains even stricter rules&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This debacle raises two philosophical questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Is Swift a hypocrite?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have musicians like Swift or photographers like Sheldon even given a compelling argument for why they&amp;rsquo;ve been treated wrongly in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do think Swift is a hypocrite, but I don&amp;rsquo;t think that it really matters because neither Swift nor Sheldon has given us a good reason to think that artists are being wronged by companies like Apple and Firefly Entertainment. Let me try to convince you to see things my way.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Ayn Rand&#39;s Psychology is Probably Wrong (or trivial)</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 05:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</guid>
      <description>Edit: Some have pointed out that I&amp;rsquo;ve misrepresented Ayn Rand&amp;rsquo;s position in this post. From what I can tell, they are right. Either way, I still think the argument presented here is interesting and accurate as long as we change the conclusion to &amp;rdquo;Psychological egoism is probably wrong (or trivial)&amp;rdquo;
I’ve met a surprising number of people in my life who believe that no one is capable of altruism. These people believe that everyone always acts to further their own interests.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>