<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>ethics on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/tags/ethics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in ethics on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 08:09:37 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/ethics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on the moral implications of building habit-forming products</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/lost-local-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 May 2019 08:09:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/lost-local-optima/</guid>
      <description>I recently finished the book Hooked: How to build habit-forming products
I challenged the author&amp;rsquo;s view on the moral permissibility of creating habit forming products here on medium (It was picked up by product coalition and selected by medium curators 🙌) and again as an interactive essay using idyll.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Selling your Soul: Notes on Gregg Pollack&#39;s Founder&#39;s Talk</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/on-selling-your-soul/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2016 08:21:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/on-selling-your-soul/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;re going to be successful, Richard, you need to learn to be an asshole.
  Erlich Bachman, Silicon Valley
 For those of you who don&amp;rsquo;t know, I was recently accepted into Starter Studio, an Orlando-based incubator to work on University Android, a codeacademy-like program for learning Android development. Every Monday night, Starter Studio brings in successful founders to talk about things they&amp;rsquo;ve learned along the way to success.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;ll Probably Try to Manipulate You</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 04:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</guid>
      <description>I became a hippie when I was a freshman in college. When I say I became a hippie, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean that I wore tie dye t-shirts all the time, smoked a lot of weed, and listened to &amp;ldquo;All you need is love&amp;rdquo; all day. I was a hippie even though I owned zero tie dye t-shirts, wasn&amp;rsquo;t cool enough to get invited to the weed parties, and had never heard that famous Beatles song that more conventional hippies love.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should the Idea Person get Extra Equity?</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 12:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my last post, I have some ideas for a startup, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to start working on them.¹ Unfortunately, doing a startup raises a lot of questions that I, as a former wannabe philosophy professor, haven&amp;rsquo;t really considered. Since its probably not a good idea to dive in to a venture that I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand, it seems like I should spend some time wrestling with what we might call &amp;ldquo;startup questions.</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
