<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startups on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startups on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>From Panic Attacks to Yoga Mats: Startups, Leadership, and my first 1000 minutes Meditating</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/my-first-1000-minutes-meditating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 09:29:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/my-first-1000-minutes-meditating/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;About a year and a half ago, I was sitting in my Manhattan studio apartment trying to write an html lexer in python. I was about half way through my batch at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.recurse.com/&#34;&gt;the Recurse Center&lt;/a&gt;, and I was frustrated with my lack of progress towards my learning goals and intimidated by all of the absurdly smart people around me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While writing the lexer, I got hung up on an odd piece of python syntax.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I spent &amp;ldquo;too long&amp;rdquo; trying to figure out what was going on with the sample code, and as a result, I felt even more frustrated by my lack of progress. I muttered a few curse words under my breath and then got ready to take another crack at my lexer code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, just as I was thinking about about how to write my code, something happened that&amp;rsquo;s never happened to me before: &lt;em&gt;My heart started racing;&lt;/em&gt; it felt like I was sprinting even though I just sitting in a chair. I felt short of breath and started sweating a bit. Then, after about a minute or so, the symptoms subsided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;☝ That was my first ever panic attack, and it freaked me out because I thought there might be something wrong with my heart. Prior to that panic attack, I&amp;rsquo;d been having chest pains for months, and I have some family history of heart issues. Fast forward a bunch of doctor&amp;rsquo;s visits, a hospital visit, and a few more panic attacks, and we found that my worry about my heart was &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; another symptom of the anxiety itself. 😌&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, I was relieved to find out that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t dying or anything, but more interestingly, I was relieved to find out that I didn&amp;rsquo;t really need to make any &lt;em&gt;deep&lt;/em&gt; changes in my behavior or thinking. I thought to myself,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;I can keep burning the midnight oil and the worst thing that&amp;rsquo;ll happen to me is a panic attack? Awesome. No problem. I don&amp;rsquo;t need to listen to people who are telling me I need to learn how to &amp;lsquo;take it easy.&amp;rsquo; I&amp;rsquo;ll just work myself up to the point where it feels like I&amp;rsquo;m going to freak out. Then I&amp;rsquo;ll take a break.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/images/1000-minutes-meditating.png&#34; alt=&#34;1000 minutes meditating&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, I completed my 1000th minute of meditation, and I know now that &amp;mdash; and this probably seems obvious to you &amp;mdash; my &amp;ldquo;work until you&amp;rsquo;re about to have a panic attack strategy&amp;rdquo; has some limitations. I&amp;rsquo;ve moved from panic attacks to yoga mats, and I want to share a bit about the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;from-panic-attacks&#34;&gt;From Panic attacks&amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Work until you&amp;rsquo;re about to have a panic attack&amp;rdquo; might obviously seem like a bad idea, but plenty of folks in silicon valley have said or presumed something like this at one point or another. Scott Galloway, an NYU Business professor and founder of L2, for example, advises:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a regular basis, at work, demonstrate both your physical and mental strength &amp;ndash; your grit. Work an eighty-hour week, be the calm one in face of stress, attack a big problem with sheer brute force and energy&amp;hellip;At Morgan Stanley, the analysis pulled all-nighters weekly, and it didn&amp;rsquo;t kill us, but made us strong. This approach to work, however, as you get older, can in fact kill you. So do it early.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham basically defines a startup in such a way that working to your limit is essential for working at a startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Economically, you can think of a startup as a way to compress your whole working life into a few years. Instead of working at a low intensity for forty years, you work as hard as you possibly can for four.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He goes on to say that a programmer working at a startup can create 3 million dollars of value per year (as opposed to the standard 80k you create working at a traditional company). To those who balk at the 3 million number, he says,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If $3 million a year seems high, remember that we&amp;rsquo;re talking about the limit case: the case where you not only have zero leisure time but indeed work so hard that you endanger your health.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:4&#34;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the idea that startups are so hard that you have to work yourself to the limits of your health is pretty much accepted by lots of smart, experienced entrepreneurs, and partially because of this, I&amp;rsquo;ve basically accepted that working an a startup is extraordinarily grindy.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:5&#34;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also think that the need for grinding hard is especially high for folks who want to be leaders at startups. Anecdotally, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that people don&amp;rsquo;t tend to work harder than their bosses (why should they?), and this intuitive idea is supported by a study or two that I&amp;rsquo;ve stumbled upon.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:6&#34;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; If succeeding at a startup requires extraordinary effort from everyone in the organization and if people don&amp;rsquo;t work harder than their leaders, then leaders have to live the grind; they have to set the pace. 🏁 🏎️&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;to-yoga-mats&#34;&gt;&amp;hellip;to Yoga Mats 🧘‍♂️&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move towards &amp;ldquo;yoga mats&amp;rdquo; started for me when I noticed that although I wasn&amp;rsquo;t working myself into having panic attacks, my anxiety and stress was leading to some extra intensity in my interactions at work. Eventually, I became convinced that this intensity made me less effective at leading.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:7&#34;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; Here&amp;rsquo;s a couple of ways this has played out in the past:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tried to convince some folks that we should not do X. We each stated our positions, and talked about it for a bit. As the conversation continued, I became more and more agitated that I wasn&amp;rsquo;t successfully convincing folks that we should not do X. The agitation was detected and people stopped taking me and my position seriously. Its like they said to themselves, &amp;ldquo;Matt is triggered. He&amp;rsquo;s not thinking clearly right now. His arguments can be safely ignored. Let&amp;rsquo;s do X,&amp;rdquo; and that&amp;rsquo;s a perfectly reasonable thought for folks to have.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I tried to convince some other folks that we should do Y. I said a bit about why I thought Y was a good idea and hoped the reasoning would stick. The problem, however, was that some folks thought the reasoning I gave was a smoke screen for something more &amp;ldquo;sinister&amp;rdquo; (read: company-oriented at the expense of employees). The impugning of my motives was no doubt partially a result of my anxious and intense stance towards work in general. People rightly worried that I don&amp;rsquo;t always have their best interests at heart. They&amp;rsquo;re right. Often this is because I&amp;rsquo;m too busy freaking out.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did some research on this and it turns out that stress and anxiety messes with your ability to &lt;em&gt;think clearly&lt;/em&gt; and to &lt;em&gt;regulate your emotions&lt;/em&gt; much more than I had expected.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:8&#34;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; So, by working through the anxiety instead of addressing it, I was trading off some short-term productivity gains for some big losses on how I communicated with people.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:9&#34;&gt;9&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After realizing I was making a bad trade off by not relaxing occasionally, I started trying to be calm by taking Sunday&amp;rsquo;s off completely. I followed everyone&amp;rsquo;s standard advice for relaxing: just do something you like doing that isn&amp;rsquo;t work. So, for a while, I mostly played &lt;em&gt;League of Legends&lt;/em&gt; to &amp;ldquo;relax.&amp;rdquo; 🎮&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks into this, I was playing one Sunday, hands tightly gripped around the mouse and cursing under my breath, and I thought, &amp;ldquo;Is this &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; relaxing? It feels good and it&amp;rsquo;s fun, but is it actually going to help me be calm when it counts?&amp;rdquo; This question turned into a quest for how I could &amp;mdash; and I get that this is weird quest &amp;mdash; &lt;em&gt;relax more efficiently&lt;/em&gt;. This is the quest that led me to start considering meditation seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was very skeptical of the effectiveness of meditation, it struck me as a potentially more efficient way of relaxing. Instead of losing my entire Sunday to gaming and other &amp;ldquo;relaxing&amp;rdquo; things, I could just set aside 10 minutes per day to meditate. Supposedly, 10 minutes a day is enough to have significant impacts on stress and anxiety levels.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:10&#34;&gt;10&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with a healthy dose of skepticism, I decided to give meditation a try for a bit by using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.headspace.com&#34;&gt;the Headspace app&lt;/a&gt;, and so far, I think the results have been pretty positive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I haven&amp;rsquo;t had any anxiety-related chest pain or GERD since I started.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been more aware of some unhelpful patterns of thought I tend to fall into, patterns which tend to waste time and produce more anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s been a few moments where I felt that I would have ordinarily interacted with others with more intensity and instead found myself simply anticipating and watching my intense emotions dissipate instead of actin&amp;rsquo; a fool.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My daily meditation habit has also helped &amp;ldquo;bootstrap&amp;rdquo; other helpful habits.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:11&#34;&gt;11&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to these &amp;ldquo;in the field benefits,&amp;rdquo; the experience of meditating is surprisingly and uniquely refreshing. Two things stand out from the experience:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, after a 10 minute session, my body feels extremely relaxed. I can tell that some of the tension I ordinarily carry around in my body has been released. My arms feel completely dead, resting on my lap. My mind also feels remarkably clear and I feel like I can focus on what needs to be done for the day.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, during the &amp;ldquo;focus on your breath&amp;rdquo; part of the exercises, I sometimes slip into a state where it actually feels like my mind is resting. Ordinarily, my mind is constantly running, thinking about myself and the past and the future. In these moments, however, I feel &amp;ldquo;present&amp;rdquo; and I&amp;rsquo;m not thinking about anything else except my breath. It feels great.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve read a bit about the changes that happen to the brain during meditation, and apparently, there&amp;rsquo;s a set of regions in the brain called &amp;ldquo;the default mode network.&amp;rdquo; 🧠 Judson Brewer, a psychiatrist whose been scientifically studying and practicing meditation for decades, calls this region the &amp;ldquo;narrative network&amp;rdquo; of the brain because its the part that is always telling a story about our past, our future, our successes, and our failures.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:12&#34;&gt;12&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; This region, according to his research, is less active during meditation and his research lines up exactly with my experience of meditation, which is reassuring because like I said, I approached meditation with a lot of skepticism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;Footnotes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;It was probably a list comprehension, but I can&amp;rsquo;t remember for sure.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Four: The Hidden DNA of Amazon, Apple, Facebook, and Google&lt;/em&gt;, pg. 252.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to Make Wealth.&amp;rdquo; Interestingly, I happened to notice Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Mean People Fail&amp;rdquo; essay while digging up this quote, and it is precisely this claim that drove me to ease up on the &amp;ldquo;work until you endanger your health&amp;rdquo; attitude.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:4&#34;&gt;Ibid. I get that working so hard you &amp;ldquo;endanger your health&amp;rdquo; is the limit case for Graham, but its the limit that we must strive for, according to Graham.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:4&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:5&#34;&gt;I think that DHH opposes the idea that startups require this kind of hard work, so he might be an exception here. He points to 37 signals as a counter-example, but I think this is problematic for several reasons. First, 37 Signals is not a startup since &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/growth.html&#34;&gt;startups are characterized&lt;/a&gt; by their rapid growth and 37 Signals is intentionally not growing quickly. Second, even if 37 Signals is a startup, their success could be an anomaly. This is not to say that they didn&amp;rsquo;t work hard, but it might be that they lucked out insofar as they were able to succeed in spite of their lack of willingness to grind as hard as other startups. To point to them as a model to follow is as wise as advising Bob to by a lottery ticket because Billy just won.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:5&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:6&#34;&gt;One study was buried in an HBR article that I can&amp;rsquo;t find right now. Basically, the study pointed out that workers&amp;rsquo; email communication outside of standard work hours mirrors the email patterns of their supervisor.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:6&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:7&#34;&gt;This realization took an embarrassingly long time. I used to excuse my &amp;ldquo;intense&amp;rdquo; attitude and not-always-mild assholery by pointing to entrepreneurs who have managed to be successful with these attitudes, entrepreneurs like Jobs, Bezos, and Musk. Two problems here: 1) I&amp;rsquo;m not nearly as brilliant as these people. I think people are more forgiving of assholery if you&amp;rsquo;re a genius. 2) Even if these guys managed to be successful, that doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that they&amp;rsquo;re successful &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; of their attitudes.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:7&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:8&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=O5HZeM6_uXI&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;The Stressed Brain&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; by Rajita Sinha was really solid here.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:8&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:9&#34;&gt;I actually think this matters a lot less for people who aren&amp;rsquo;t aspiring leaders. Interestingly, a lot of the examples that I&amp;rsquo;ve seen about how grindy things can be at startups seems to focus around individual contributors. We definitely see this in Paul Graham&amp;rsquo;s example. Its about a programmer who&amp;rsquo;s just trying to grind out some code. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter if he gets pissed at his computer in the process. &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2018/02/senior-executives-get-more-sleep-than-everyone-else&#34;&gt;The hbr article I stumbled across a few weeks ago about how executives tend to get more sleep than individual contributors&lt;/a&gt; also points in this direction.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:9&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:10&#34;&gt;I believe this is mentioned in &amp;ldquo;The Stressed Brain&amp;rdquo; video, but its also mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ted.com/talks/andy_puddicombe_all_it_takes_is_10_mindful_minutes&#34;&gt;this TED talk&lt;/a&gt; and in &lt;a href=&#34;https://hbr.org/2017/01/spending-10-minutes-a-day-on-mindfulness-subtly-changes-the-way-you-react-to-everything&#34;&gt;this HBR article&lt;/a&gt;.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:10&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:11&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if its the meditation habit itself that&amp;rsquo;s doing the work here. Stress and anxiety compromise the executive functioning of the brain, so it might be that the stress reduction that results from meditation has improved my executive functioning, which in turn has made space for me to adopt other helpful habits.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:11&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:12&#34;&gt;Judson Brewer, &lt;em&gt;The Craving Mind&lt;/em&gt;, xvi.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:12&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TDD and Startups</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 13:32:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Kent Beck introduces &lt;em&gt;TDD by Example&lt;/em&gt; with a little story meant to show the business value of automated testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early one Friday, the boss came to Ward Cunningham to introduce him to Peter, a prospective customer for WyCash, the bond portfolio management system the company was selling. Peter said&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new bond fund, and my strategy requires that I handle bonds in different currencies.” The boss turned to Ward, “Well, can we do it?&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;The trick now was to make space for the new functionality without breaking anything that already worked. What would happen if Ward just ran the tests? After the addition of a few unimplemented operations to Currency, the bulk of the tests passed. By the end of the day, all of the tests were passing. Ward checked the code into the build and went to the boss. “We can do it,” he said confidently. Let&amp;rsquo;s think a bit about this story. In two days, the potential market was multiplied several fold, multiplying the value of WyCash several fold. The ability to create so much business value so quickly was no accident, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little parable actually reminded me of the way that Steve Freeman and Nat Pryce talk about the business value of automated testing in &lt;em&gt;Growing Object Oriented Software Guided by Tests&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve found that we need two technical foundations if we want to grow a system reliably and to cope with the unanticipated changes that always happen. First, we need constant testing to catch regression errors, so we can add new features without breaking existing ones. For systems of any interesting size, frequent manual testing is just impractical&amp;hellip;Second, we need to keep the code as simple as possible, so it’s easier to understand and modify&amp;hellip;The test suites in the feedback loops protect us against our own mistakes as we improve (and therefore change) the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these two snippets are making similar points: automated tests can create immense business value because it allows deep changes to be made to an existing system while preserving confidence that the system will continue working as expected. I think this ability is especially important for startups who are trying to find product-market fit or beat out a competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sometimes suspect that Facebook&amp;rsquo;s success over Friendster and MySpace is partially due to the fact that they had the automated tests in place to experiment a ton with the features of Facebook and that these experiments let them iterate faster (Zuckerberg actually talks about this in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lb4IcGF5iTQ&#34;&gt;his &amp;ldquo;How to Build the Future&amp;rdquo; episode&lt;/a&gt;). Iterating faster, according to Eric Reis in &lt;em&gt;The Lean Startup&lt;/em&gt;, isn&amp;rsquo;t just the key to maximizing chances of building something people want. It&amp;rsquo;s also a great way to gain a competitive edge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason to build a new team to pursue an idea is that you believe you can accelerate through the Build-Measure-Learn feedback loop faster than anyone else can. If that’s true, it makes no difference what the competition knows. If it’s not true, a startup has much bigger problems&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually think this is one of the most under-rated arguments for TDD. When considering whether to write tests, I suspect a lot of developers think, &amp;ldquo;Well, I can get it working without tests, so why bother writing them?&amp;rdquo; Unfortunately, this overlooks the key issue, which, if Beck, Freeman and Pryce, and Reis are right, is this: &amp;ldquo;How can I structure my system so that I can make the biggest possible changes while maintaining confidence that the functionality is correct?&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; If TDD folks are right, moreover, the answer to this key question is of course to do TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If this is right, then it means that a comment that Beck makes later on in the first part of TDD by Example may need refinement. He says:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For TDD to make economic sense, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to be able to either write twice as many lines per day as before, or write half as many lines for the same functionality. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to measure and see what effect TDD has on your own practice. Be sure to factor debugging, integrating, and explaining time into your metrics, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This remark may in fact be consistent with the idea that there&amp;rsquo;s immense value in the flexible architectures that emerge as a result of TDD. Its hard to tell exactly what Beck is saying here. Beck&amp;rsquo;s intent aside, I think this passage should have made it clearer that there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of value in being able to change code confidently, and this may make TDD worth it even if we wind up writing more code when we factor in the code we need to write tests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes&#34;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, if you&amp;rsquo;re not building a product whose features are likely to change, then this argument for testing doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should the Idea Person get Extra Equity?</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 12:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/21/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/&#34;&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt;, I have some ideas for a startup, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to start working on them.¹ Unfortunately, doing a startup raises a lot of questions that I, as a former wannabe philosophy professor, haven&amp;rsquo;t really considered. Since its probably not a good idea to dive in to a venture that I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand, it seems like I should spend some time wrestling with what we might call &amp;ldquo;startup questions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wrestling with a startup question that I hope will be interesting to the startup community in general:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should the &amp;ldquo;idea person&amp;rdquo; get more equity than the other co-founders &lt;em&gt;simply because&lt;/em&gt; the startup is based on her idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we wrestle with this question, let me say a little more to clarify exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m asking here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m asking whether having a good idea is itself a sufficient reason to get more equity. In other words, I&amp;rsquo;m asking if all other contributions are equal among co-founders, should the idea co-founder get extra equity? Or, to put the question a third way, I&amp;rsquo;m wondering whether it would make sense to give a person some equity for coming up with a good startup idea even if that person contributed nothing else to the success of the startup.²&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional answer to this question seems to be &amp;ldquo;yes.&amp;ldquo;³ Now, if it turns out that convention is correct and that the idea person should get some extra equity, this would be sweet for me because at this point, I suspect that I&amp;rsquo;ll be an idea person for my startup. Unfortunately, I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that I should get extra equity simply for having an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s are two reasons I&amp;rsquo;m hesitant to call &amp;ldquo;moral dibs&amp;rdquo; on my extra idea-person-equity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I don&amp;rsquo;t really feel responsible for the generation of my startup ideas. I didn&amp;rsquo;t sit around and think hard about &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; that I could solve with a company. The ideas just sort of came to me.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Since I didn&amp;rsquo;t really do any work to generate my startup ideas, it feels weird to get rewarded for it. For me, being rewarded for one of my startup ideas would kind of feel like getting rewarded for having a bowel movement. My response to such a prize would be, &amp;ldquo;Thanks for the reward, but this shit sort of just happened.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A corollary of this point is that I&amp;rsquo;d have no problem demanding extra equity if I put a lot of work into coming up with a good idea. If I, for example, researched the various problems that industries or individuals are facing and used this information to come up with a startup idea, then I&amp;rsquo;d feel totally justified in asking for equity. In this case, however, I&amp;rsquo;m not getting equity simply for having an idea. Rather, I&amp;rsquo;m getting equity for work that I put into generating a good idea.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced I should get extra equity is that I haven&amp;rsquo;t really come across any solid arguments to the contrary. In fact, the only real argument I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered seems to go something like:  &amp;ldquo;Without the idea guy, the startup wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be possible, so the idea guy should definitely get more equity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s got to be more to this argument if its going to be compelling. As it stands, the argument seems to assume that if a person makes a startup possible, then that person should get equity. That assumption is probably false since presumably we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t give equity to the idea guy&amp;rsquo;s parents, even though the startup wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be possible without the parent&amp;rsquo;s decision to bring an entrepreneur-child into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those two reasons, I don&amp;rsquo;t think that the idea person should get extra equity. Some might see this as kind of a radical position. It probably is, but don&amp;rsquo;t be offended. I&amp;rsquo;ve only thought about this question for an hour and I&amp;rsquo;m not even a &amp;ldquo;real entrepreneur&amp;rdquo; yet, so I&amp;rsquo;m very open to being wrong about this.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; Feel free to tell me I&amp;rsquo;m wrong or to tell me how you think about equity splits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can check them out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.launchyourstudents.co&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tangoisfantastic.appspot.com&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The second idea is only half mine. The other half belongs to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/manuel.arredondo?fref=ts&#34;&gt;Manuel Arredondo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, idea people may have other qualities that will earn them a larger share of the equity, but I&amp;rsquo;m not interested in those qualities. It might turn out, for example, that idea people are often more passionate about their startups and that this passion helps them work harder than other co-founders. If idea people tend to work harder, then it seems clear that they should get more equity &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they work harder, but I&amp;rsquo;m not asking whether idea people who happen to work harder should get a higher equity share.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 152nd page of his book &lt;em&gt;The Founder&amp;rsquo;s Dilemmas&lt;/em&gt;, Noam Wasserman reports that startups typically give the idea guy an extra 10-15% equity. Wasserman  suspects that a part of the equity is given for &amp;ldquo;past contributions&amp;rdquo; (including the idea itself) and part of the equity is given out of &amp;ldquo;recognition that the idea person might be more likely to contribute important additional ideas in the future.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/startupideas.html&#34;&gt;According to Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt;, this is actually how it usually happens. Elizabeth Gilbert also thinks that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_on_genius&#34;&gt;this is how ideas are generated for authors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its possible that there&amp;rsquo;s something fishing going on with this distinction. Unfortunately, I don&amp;rsquo;t have time to address worries about this right now. If you don&amp;rsquo;t like my position, this distinction might be a good place to criticize me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the founders at Crimson Solutions seemed to make an argument like this. Wasserman, &lt;em&gt;The Founder&amp;rsquo;s Dilemmas&lt;/em&gt;, 152.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scare quotes are for readers who don&amp;rsquo;t really like how I&amp;rsquo;m defining &amp;ldquo;real entrepreneur&amp;rdquo; in this sentence. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, there&amp;rsquo;s no need to get philosophical. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to define the term &amp;ldquo;entrepreneur.&amp;rdquo; All I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say is that I&amp;rsquo;m not working full time on a startup.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>