<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startups on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startups on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 13:32:57 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>TDD and Startups</title>
      <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 13:32:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Beck introduces &lt;em&gt;TDD by Example&lt;/em&gt; with a little story meant to show the business value of automated testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Early one Friday, the boss came to Ward Cunningham to introduce him to Peter, a prospective customer for WyCash, the bond portfolio management system the company was selling. Peter said&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new bond fund, and my strategy requires that I handle bonds in different currencies.” The boss turned to Ward, “Well, can we do it?&amp;rdquo;&amp;hellip;The trick now was to make space for the new functionality without breaking anything that already worked. What would happen if Ward just ran the tests? After the addition of a few unimplemented operations to Currency, the bulk of the tests passed. By the end of the day, all of the tests were passing. Ward checked the code into the build and went to the boss. “We can do it,” he said confidently. Let&amp;rsquo;s think a bit about this story. In two days, the potential market was multiplied several fold, multiplying the value of WyCash several fold. The ability to create so much business value so quickly was no accident, however.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This little parable actually reminded me of the way that Steve Freeman and Nat Pryce talk about the business value of automated testing in &lt;em&gt;Growing Object Oriented Software Guided by Tests&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve found that we need two technical foundations if we want to grow a system reliably and to cope with the unanticipated changes that always happen. First, we need constant testing to catch regression errors, so we can add new features without breaking existing ones. For systems of any interesting size, frequent manual testing is just impractical&amp;hellip;Second, we need to keep the code as simple as possible, so it’s easier to understand and modify&amp;hellip;The test suites in the feedback loops protect us against our own mistakes as we improve (and therefore change) the code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think these two snippets are making similar points: automated tests can create immense business value because it allows deep changes to be made to an existing system while preserving confidence that the system will continue working as expected. I think this ability is especially important for startups who are trying to find product-market fit or beat out a competitor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sometimes suspect that Facebook&amp;rsquo;s success over Friendster and MySpace is partially due to the fact that they had the automated tests in place to experiment a ton with the features of Facebook and that these experiments let them iterate faster (Zuckerberg actually talks about this in &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Lb4IcGF5iTQ&#34;&gt;his &amp;ldquo;How to Build the Future&amp;rdquo; episode&lt;/a&gt;). Iterating faster, according to Eric Reis in &lt;em&gt;The Lean Startup&lt;/em&gt;, isn&amp;rsquo;t just the key to maximizing chances of building something people want. It&amp;rsquo;s also a great way to gain a competitive edge:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reason to build a new team to pursue an idea is that you believe you can accelerate through the Build-Measure-Learn feedback loop faster than anyone else can. If that’s true, it makes no difference what the competition knows. If it’s not true, a startup has much bigger problems&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I actually think this is one of the most under-rated arguments for TDD. When considering whether to write tests, I suspect a lot of developers think, &amp;ldquo;Well, I can get it working without tests, so why bother writing them?&amp;rdquo; Unfortunately, this overlooks the key issue, which, if Beck, Freeman and Pryce, and Reis are right, is this: &amp;ldquo;How can I structure my system so that I can make the biggest possible changes while maintaining confidence that the functionality is correct?&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt; If TDD folks are right, moreover, the answer to this key question is of course to do TDD.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;notes:758ef2c35412a7b4b3fc0c0663789a9e&#34;&gt;Notes:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Of course, if you&amp;rsquo;re not building a product whose features are likely to change, then this argument for testing doesn&amp;rsquo;t apply.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should the Idea Person get Extra Equity?</title>
      <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 12:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/21/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/&#34;&gt;my last post&lt;/a&gt;, I have some ideas for a startup, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to start working on them.¹ Unfortunately, doing a startup raises a lot of questions that I, as a former wannabe philosophy professor, haven&amp;rsquo;t really considered. Since its probably not a good idea to dive in to a venture that I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand, it seems like I should spend some time wrestling with what we might call &amp;ldquo;startup questions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lately, I&amp;rsquo;ve been wrestling with a startup question that I hope will be interesting to the startup community in general:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should the &amp;ldquo;idea person&amp;rdquo; get more equity than the other co-founders &lt;em&gt;simply because&lt;/em&gt; the startup is based on her idea?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we wrestle with this question, let me say a little more to clarify exactly what I&amp;rsquo;m asking here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m asking whether having a good idea is itself a sufficient reason to get more equity. In other words, I&amp;rsquo;m asking if all other contributions are equal among co-founders, should the idea co-founder get extra equity? Or, to put the question a third way, I&amp;rsquo;m wondering whether it would make sense to give a person some equity for coming up with a good startup idea even if that person contributed nothing else to the success of the startup.²&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conventional answer to this question seems to be &amp;ldquo;yes.&amp;ldquo;³ Now, if it turns out that convention is correct and that the idea person should get some extra equity, this would be sweet for me because at this point, I suspect that I&amp;rsquo;ll be an idea person for my startup. Unfortunately, I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced that I should get extra equity simply for having an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s are two reasons I&amp;rsquo;m hesitant to call &amp;ldquo;moral dibs&amp;rdquo; on my extra idea-person-equity:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I don&amp;rsquo;t really feel responsible for the generation of my startup ideas. I didn&amp;rsquo;t sit around and think hard about &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; that I could solve with a company. The ideas just sort of came to me.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; Since I didn&amp;rsquo;t really do any work to generate my startup ideas, it feels weird to get rewarded for it. For me, being rewarded for one of my startup ideas would kind of feel like getting rewarded for having a bowel movement. My response to such a prize would be, &amp;ldquo;Thanks for the reward, but this shit sort of just happened.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A corollary of this point is that I&amp;rsquo;d have no problem demanding extra equity if I put a lot of work into coming up with a good idea. If I, for example, researched the various problems that industries or individuals are facing and used this information to come up with a startup idea, then I&amp;rsquo;d feel totally justified in asking for equity. In this case, however, I&amp;rsquo;m not getting equity simply for having an idea. Rather, I&amp;rsquo;m getting equity for work that I put into generating a good idea.&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second reason I&amp;rsquo;m not convinced I should get extra equity is that I haven&amp;rsquo;t really come across any solid arguments to the contrary. In fact, the only real argument I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered seems to go something like:  &amp;ldquo;Without the idea guy, the startup wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be possible, so the idea guy should definitely get more equity.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s got to be more to this argument if its going to be compelling. As it stands, the argument seems to assume that if a person makes a startup possible, then that person should get equity. That assumption is probably false since presumably we wouldn&amp;rsquo;t give equity to the idea guy&amp;rsquo;s parents, even though the startup wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be possible without the parent&amp;rsquo;s decision to bring an entrepreneur-child into the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those two reasons, I don&amp;rsquo;t think that the idea person should get extra equity. Some might see this as kind of a radical position. It probably is, but don&amp;rsquo;t be offended. I&amp;rsquo;ve only thought about this question for an hour and I&amp;rsquo;m not even a &amp;ldquo;real entrepreneur&amp;rdquo; yet, so I&amp;rsquo;m very open to being wrong about this.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt; Feel free to tell me I&amp;rsquo;m wrong or to tell me how you think about equity splits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can check them out &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.launchyourstudents.co&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tangoisfantastic.appspot.com&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. The second idea is only half mine. The other half belongs to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/manuel.arredondo?fref=ts&#34;&gt;Manuel Arredondo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Of course, idea people may have other qualities that will earn them a larger share of the equity, but I&amp;rsquo;m not interested in those qualities. It might turn out, for example, that idea people are often more passionate about their startups and that this passion helps them work harder than other co-founders. If idea people tend to work harder, then it seems clear that they should get more equity &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; they work harder, but I&amp;rsquo;m not asking whether idea people who happen to work harder should get a higher equity share.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;On the 152nd page of his book &lt;em&gt;The Founder&amp;rsquo;s Dilemmas&lt;/em&gt;, Noam Wasserman reports that startups typically give the idea guy an extra 10-15% equity. Wasserman  suspects that a part of the equity is given for &amp;ldquo;past contributions&amp;rdquo; (including the idea itself) and part of the equity is given out of &amp;ldquo;recognition that the idea person might be more likely to contribute important additional ideas in the future.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://paulgraham.com/startupideas.html&#34;&gt;According to Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt;, this is actually how it usually happens. Elizabeth Gilbert also thinks that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ted.com/talks/elizabeth_gilbert_on_genius&#34;&gt;this is how ideas are generated for authors&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Its possible that there&amp;rsquo;s something fishing going on with this distinction. Unfortunately, I don&amp;rsquo;t have time to address worries about this right now. If you don&amp;rsquo;t like my position, this distinction might be a good place to criticize me.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;One of the founders at Crimson Solutions seemed to make an argument like this. Wasserman, &lt;em&gt;The Founder&amp;rsquo;s Dilemmas&lt;/em&gt;, 152.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The scare quotes are for readers who don&amp;rsquo;t really like how I&amp;rsquo;m defining &amp;ldquo;real entrepreneur&amp;rdquo; in this sentence. Don&amp;rsquo;t worry, there&amp;rsquo;s no need to get philosophical. I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to define the term &amp;ldquo;entrepreneur.&amp;rdquo; All I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say is that I&amp;rsquo;m not working full time on a startup.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>