<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Startups on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Startups on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 19:29:05 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/startups/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>How Passion for Programming Can Make us Worse at our Jobs</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/programmer-passion-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 19:29:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/programmer-passion-worse/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Good programmers are passionate about what they do&amp;rdquo; is basically a platitude in our industry. 🙄 On the whole, this may be true, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in how our passion for programming might get in the way of us doing well for the companies we work for and may even lead to us being worse at programming specifically. 🤔
Here are some ways I think this passion can make us worse at what we do:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Panic Attacks to Yoga Mats: Startups, Leadership, and my first 1000 minutes Meditating</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/my-first-1000-minutes-meditating/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Mar 2018 09:29:59 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/my-first-1000-minutes-meditating/</guid>
      <description>About a year and a half ago, I was sitting in my Manhattan studio apartment trying to write an html lexer in python. I was about half way through my batch at the Recurse Center, and I was frustrated with my lack of progress towards my learning goals and intimidated by all of the absurdly smart people around me.
While writing the lexer, I got hung up on an odd piece of python syntax.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>TDD and Startups</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 13:32:57 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/tdd-and-startups/</guid>
      <description>Kent Beck introduces TDD by Example with a little story meant to show the business value of automated testing:
 Early one Friday, the boss came to Ward Cunningham to introduce him to Peter, a prospective customer for WyCash, the bond portfolio management system the company was selling. Peter said&amp;hellip;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m starting a new bond fund, and my strategy requires that I handle bonds in different currencies.” The boss turned to Ward, “Well, can we do it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should the Idea Person get Extra Equity?</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Apr 2014 12:17:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/</guid>
      <description>As I mentioned in my last post, I have some ideas for a startup, and I&amp;rsquo;m excited to start working on them.¹ Unfortunately, doing a startup raises a lot of questions that I, as a former wannabe philosophy professor, haven&amp;rsquo;t really considered. Since its probably not a good idea to dive in to a venture that I don&amp;rsquo;t really understand, it seems like I should spend some time wrestling with what we might call &amp;ldquo;startup questions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>