<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Product Management on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/product-management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Product Management on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 10:55:05 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/product-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hilarious Heresy: A Review of Jessica Powell’s &#34;The Big Disruption&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/big-disruption-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Mar 2019 10:55:05 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/big-disruption-review/</guid>
      <description>If I had to pick a few words to describe Jessica Powell’s The Big Disruption they’d be the words “hilarious heresy.”
&amp;ldquo;Hilarious&amp;rdquo; because the book is surprisingly funny. My wife actually kept commenting on how much I was chuckling as I read the book.
&amp;ldquo;Heresy&amp;rdquo; because it’s a good way of capturing what Powell is doing in the book with all of her criticisms: she’s challenging the silicon valley gospel that tech companies are here to save the world, and given all of the attention and good will towards those companies, “heresy” feels like an appropriate label for this message.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some problems with the impossibility of achieving OKRs</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/okr-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 22:11:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/okr-problems/</guid>
      <description>In many ways, OKRs are a neat way of structuring goals for a company. According to Marty Cagan, product managers should be especially interested in OKRs as a goal setting framework since they are a better way of tracking product work than a &amp;ldquo;product roadmap.&amp;rdquo; I agree with Cagan. OKRs are often better than typical product road maps.
However, there’s an aspect of OKRs that I think is morally and psychologically problematic: the idea that OKRs should be impossible to entirely achieve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How The Lean Principle Became Profound</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/how-lean-became-profound/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Feb 2019 14:18:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/how-lean-became-profound/</guid>
      <description>There are certain books that are required reading for product managers. Eric Reis&amp;rsquo; The Lean Startup and Marty Cagan&amp;rsquo;s Inspired both come to mind. They&amp;rsquo;re great books with lots of useful techniques and important ideas.
Lately, however, the fact that these books are popular and useful has struck me as rather odd. If you take a step back from these books &amp;mdash; and the many books, articles, talks, podcasts, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Startups Can Do Better Cohort Analyses</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/better-cohort-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 07:48:17 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/better-cohort-analysis/</guid>
      <description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever looked at analytics for software products, you&amp;rsquo;ve probably run across a graph that looks like this:
Graphs like this one depict cohort analyses.1 This particular graph is from Google Analytics. Apple also has one for app analytics. So does Fabric.2
Cohort analyses can be very useful. For example, Eric Reis, in The Lean Startup, recounts how cohort analysis helped his startup realize that their efforts at improving their product weren&amp;rsquo;t working:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>