<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>programming on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in programming on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 20:30:56 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Mid-Career Job-Hunt: A Data Point for Job-Seeking Devs</title>
      <link>/post/data-point-for-job-seeking-devs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2020 20:30:56 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/data-point-for-job-seeking-devs/</guid>
      <description>I wrapped up my job search recently, and I&amp;rsquo;m happy to say that I&amp;rsquo;ll be joining a YC-backed startup called &amp;ldquo;Heap.&amp;rdquo; I thought I&amp;rsquo;d share a little bit about my job search in case the information may benefit other job-seeking devs. I&amp;rsquo;ll go over the pipeline of places I applied to and the result of each application. I&amp;rsquo;ll also talk about things like salary, resume formatting, coding challenge prep, and interviewing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maybe Don&#39;t Inject That</title>
      <link>/post/maybe-dont-inject-that/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2019 19:27:36 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/maybe-dont-inject-that/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m actually always suspicious when I&amp;rsquo;m writing up a pattern or a technique if I can&amp;rsquo;t talk about reasons when you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t use and trade-offs against it. If I can&amp;rsquo;t find arguments against it, then I&amp;rsquo;m worrying that I&amp;rsquo;m not really analyzing things properly.
&amp;ndash;Martin Fowler, &amp;ldquo;Is TDD Dead?&amp;rdquo;, 35:00
 DI is useful. It&amp;rsquo;s great. It makes your code more flexible, testable, etc. Dagger? Also useful. Great. My favorite DI library.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maybe Don&#39;t Write That Test</title>
      <link>/post/maybe-dont-write-that-test/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2019 09:08:53 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/maybe-dont-write-that-test/</guid>
      <description>Testing seems to be like going to gym. Everyone feels like &amp;ldquo;yeah. I should be testing. I should be going to the gym everyday.&amp;rdquo;
Koushik Goupal, Fragmented, &amp;ldquo;Episode 13,&amp;rdquo; 12:01
 Remember those gimmicky fitness products that made you think you could &amp;ldquo;get fit&amp;rdquo; without actually going to the gym/dieting/etc? Because I live in Orlando and have seen the Carousel of Progress at the Magic Kingdom a bunch of times, the first example of this kind of gimmicky product that comes to mind is a thing called an &amp;ldquo;exercise belt.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dagger 2, 2 Years Later</title>
      <link>/post/dagger-2-years-later/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2019 19:27:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/dagger-2-years-later/</guid>
      <description>&amp;hellip;in software, feedback cycles tend to be on the order of months, if not years&amp;hellip;It’s during the full lifetime of a project that a developer gains experience writing code, source controlling it, modifying it, testing it, and living with previous design and architecture decisions during maintenance phases. With everything I’ve just described, a developer is lucky to have a first try of less than six months&amp;hellip;
&amp;ndash;Erik Dietrich, &amp;ldquo;How Developers Stop Learning: Rise of the Expert Beginner&amp;rdquo;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maybe we Should Stop Creating Inscrutable CLIs</title>
      <link>/post/towards-readable-clis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Aug 2019 10:45:06 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/towards-readable-clis/</guid>
      <description>In the original Unix tradition, command-line options are single letters preceded by a single hyphen&amp;hellip;The original Unix style evolved on slow ASR-33 teletypes that made terseness a virtue; thus the single-letter options.
Eric Steven Raymond, The Art of Unix Programming
  Programs must be written for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute.
Abelson et. al., Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs
 I just wrote this little bash-ism the other day for removing all attachments from a jira ticket:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Passion for Programming Can Make us Worse at our Jobs</title>
      <link>/post/programmer-passion-worse/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 19:29:05 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/programmer-passion-worse/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Good programmers are passionate about what they do&amp;rdquo; is basically a platitude in our industry. 🙄 On the whole, this may be true, but lately I&amp;rsquo;ve been interested in how our passion for programming might get in the way of us doing well for the companies we work for and may even lead to us being worse at programming specifically. 🤔
Here are some ways I think this passion can make us worse at what we do:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on how to teach programming</title>
      <link>/post/teaching-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 09:43:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/teaching-programming/</guid>
      <description>I almost gave up on becoming a programmer. I took two years of college-level programming in high school and I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly care for it. Although I did fairly well in those classes, at the time, I probably had something like the following thoughts about programming:
 I&amp;rsquo;ve given this a fair shake. I&amp;rsquo;ve taken two years of classes, and I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that programming is some tedious bullshit 💩. I need to find something else.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacker vs. Hustler: Reflecting on One Year at UniKey</title>
      <link>/post/hacker-vs-hustler-reflecting-on-one-year-at-unikey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 18:33:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/hacker-vs-hustler-reflecting-on-one-year-at-unikey/</guid>
      <description>Me: I really like my new job.
Family: (incredulously) Really?
Me: Yeah. The people are smart, passionate, and the company seems promising.
Family: (sarcastically) Ok. So you&amp;rsquo;ll stick around for 6 months then?
 Two Wednesdays ago marked my 1 year anniversary at UniKey, and as the above dialog suggests, this is pretty weird for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve never been at a job for a year before, so this 1st ever anniversary in my career has given me the urge to reflect a bit on a couple of questions:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Ayn Rand&#39;s Psychology is Probably Wrong (or trivial)</title>
      <link>/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 05:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</guid>
      <description>Edit: Some have pointed out that I&amp;rsquo;ve misrepresented Ayn Rand&amp;rsquo;s position in this post. From what I can tell, they are right. Either way, I still think the argument presented here is interesting and accurate as long as we change the conclusion to &amp;rdquo;Psychological egoism is probably wrong (or trivial)&amp;rdquo;
I’ve met a surprising number of people in my life who believe that no one is capable of altruism. These people believe that everyone always acts to further their own interests.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>