<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/programming/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Programming on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 09:43:30 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/programming/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on how to teach programming</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/teaching-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2018 09:43:30 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/teaching-programming/</guid>
      <description>I almost gave up on becoming a programmer. I took two years of college-level programming in high school and I didn&amp;rsquo;t particularly care for it. Although I did fairly well in those classes, at the time, I probably had something like the following thoughts about programming:
 I&amp;rsquo;ve given this a fair shake. I&amp;rsquo;ve taken two years of classes, and I&amp;rsquo;ve decided that programming is some tedious bullshit 💩. I need to find something else.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hacker vs. Hustler: Reflecting on One Year at UniKey</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/hacker-vs-hustler-reflecting-on-one-year-at-unikey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2017 18:33:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/hacker-vs-hustler-reflecting-on-one-year-at-unikey/</guid>
      <description>Me: I really like my new job.
Family: (incredulously) Really?
Me: Yeah. The people are smart, passionate, and the company seems promising.
Family: (sarcastically) Ok. So you&amp;rsquo;ll stick around for 6 months then?
 Two Wednesdays ago marked my 1 year anniversary at UniKey, and as the above dialog suggests, this is pretty weird for me. I&amp;rsquo;ve never been at a job for a year before, so this 1st ever anniversary in my career has given me the urge to reflect a bit on a couple of questions:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Ayn Rand&#39;s Psychology is Probably Wrong (or trivial)</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 05:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</guid>
      <description>Edit: Some have pointed out that I&amp;rsquo;ve misrepresented Ayn Rand&amp;rsquo;s position in this post. From what I can tell, they are right. Either way, I still think the argument presented here is interesting and accurate as long as we change the conclusion to &amp;rdquo;Psychological egoism is probably wrong (or trivial)&amp;rdquo;
I’ve met a surprising number of people in my life who believe that no one is capable of altruism. These people believe that everyone always acts to further their own interests.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>