<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Ayn Rand&#39;s Psychology is Probably Wrong (or trivial)</title>
      <link>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Jan 2015 05:20:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2015/01/24/why-ayn-rands-psychology-is-probably-wrong/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit: &lt;/strong&gt;Some have pointed out that I&amp;rsquo;ve misrepresented Ayn Rand&amp;rsquo;s position in this post. From what I can tell, they are right. Either way, I still think the argument presented here is interesting and accurate as long as we change the conclusion to &amp;rdquo;Psychological egoism is probably wrong (or trivial)&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve met a surprising number of people in my life who believe that no one is capable of altruism. These people believe that &lt;em&gt;everyone&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; acts to further their own interests. Many of these people are influenced by Ayn Rand. Back in my philosophy grad student days, we called these people “psychological egoists” and we called the thesis they endorse “psychological egoism.” I think that psychological egoism is either false or trivially true. This is the first of a (two part?) blog series in which I argue for this claim. In this first part of the series, I simply draw a (hacker friendly) distinction between &amp;ldquo;trivial truth&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;empirical truth&amp;rdquo; and I use this distinction to clarify my central claim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;two-kinds-of-truth&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Two Kinds of Truth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve just said that I want to argue psychological egoism is either false or &amp;ldquo;trivially true.&amp;rdquo; My argument won’t be very convincing if we aren’t clear what claim I’m arguing for in the first place, so let’s take some time to make a distinction between two kinds of truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;trivial-truth&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trivial Truth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean when I say that something is &amp;ldquo;trivially true?&amp;rdquo; To get a grip on what I mean by this phrase, let&amp;rsquo;s think for a second about something that we do everyday when we&amp;rsquo;re writing code: we define constants. &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-10-27-57-pm.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-10-27-57-pm.png?w=660&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2015-01-23 at 10.27.57 PM&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; When we define a constant, we simply &lt;em&gt;stipulate&lt;/em&gt; that an constant is equivalent to some literal value. Because we’ve stipulated that &lt;code&gt;TRIANGLE&lt;/code&gt; is equal to &lt;code&gt;“three sided figure,”&lt;/code&gt; any call to &lt;code&gt;isTriangleAThreeSidedFigure()&lt;/code&gt; will &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt;. More importantly, &lt;code&gt;isTriangleAThreeSidedFigure()&lt;/code&gt; will always return &lt;code&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; because of a stipulation that we made earlier in the code. Because of this, calling &lt;code&gt;isTriangleAThreeSidedFigure()&lt;/code&gt; is pretty much a waste of time. You would never write a method like this. Analogously, we’d think that anyone who asks “Is a triangle &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; a three sided figure?,” is just trying to waste our time. We’d reply with, “Did you miss the part in elementary school where we just defined a triangle as a three sided figure?” Moreover, we’d think that anyone who wanted to deny that a triangle was a three sided figure was just choosing to use his words differently. Returning to our coding analogy, we’d treat them as if their source code looked like this: &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-10-46-46-pm.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-10-46-46-pm.png?w=660&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2015-01-23 at 10.46.46 PM&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; If &lt;code&gt;TRANGLE&lt;/code&gt; is defined as a &lt;code&gt;“four sided figure,”&lt;/code&gt; then (obviously) &lt;code&gt;isTrangleAThreeSidedFigure()&lt;/code&gt; will return &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt;, but the method that we’ve written here is equally pointless. We know that it’ll return &lt;code&gt;false&lt;/code&gt; because of how we defined &lt;code&gt;TRIANGLE&lt;/code&gt; above. Similarly, if someone wants to redefine the word “triangle” and then proceed to claim that a triangle is not a three-sided figure, arguing with them is pointless. They’ve defined their words so that their claim turns out to be true, so at that point we can say, “Hey, man. Use your words however you want. I’m interested in talking about non-trivial truths.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;empirical-truth&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Empirical Truth&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s another kind of truth that’s more interesting. Some claims are true because they “match up” with the world rather than with our own stipulations. &amp;ldquo;Alan Turing is dead,&amp;rdquo; for example, is a claim that isn’t true by definition. In other words, we haven’t stipulated that the name “Alan Turring” _means _“dead guy.” *&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-11-04-27-pm.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-23-at-11-04-27-pm.png?w=660&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2015-01-23 at 11.04.27 PM&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;**&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;* If we want to know whether Alan Turring is dead, we look around and we do some research. In short, we ask the world, “Is Alan Turring really dead?” &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-24-at-12-13-57-am.png&#34;&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://www.philosophicalhacker.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/01/screen-shot-2015-01-24-at-12-13-57-am.png?w=660&#34; alt=&#34;Screen Shot 2015-01-24 at 12.13.57 AM&#34; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; The return value for Bob’s &lt;code&gt;isAlanTurringDead()&lt;/code&gt; call depends on the return value for the identically named method on &lt;code&gt;TheWorldInWhichWeLive&lt;/code&gt;. It does not depend on any sort of stipulation that Bob (or any other human) came up with. Because of this calling &lt;code&gt;isAlanTurringDead()&lt;/code&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t (obviously) pointless. The return value for &lt;code&gt;isAlanTurringDead()&lt;/code&gt; may be interesting and surprising. Again, the above code illustrates how we actually think about truth in our conversations: If someone claimed that Alan Turring is still alive, we’d certainly want to know what evidence they had for that claim. Unlike the claim that a triangle is a three sided figure, the claim that Alan Turring is still alive is interesting and worth discussing. To sum it up: empirical truths are about the world and they’re interesting to debate. Trivial truths are truths &lt;em&gt;merely&lt;/em&gt; because of the definitions of our terms and they aren’t that interesting to debate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so-whats-my-claim-again&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, whats my claim again?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’re clear on the distinction between trivial and empirical truths, we’re in a better position to appreciate the thesis for which I’m arguing. Again, that thesis is this: &lt;strong&gt;Psychological egoism is either (empirically) false or trivially true.&lt;/strong&gt; In other words, psychological egoism is either an interesting, albeit false claim or its an uninteresting trivial claim that’s true merely in virtue of the definition of the terms used to express it. Let’s flesh this claim out a bit more by thinking again about the claim that Alan Turing is alive. Clearly this claim is false, but suppose that I was debating with someone about this. The first thing I’d do is show them &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alan_Turing&#34;&gt;the wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt; that clearly shows that Alan Turing is dead. Now, let’s suppose that my interlocutor responded with the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Well, that article doesn’t really show that Alan Turing is dead! The word “dead” really means “no longer breathing and buried underground.” Since Alan Turing was cremated, he’s not really dead!&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If someone responded this way, I’d feel that he was cheating in the debate, and I suspect that you’d feel the same way. I think we’d feel this way because we thought we were discussing a controversial, empirical claim about the world and because we were disappointed to find out that we were disagreeing simply because we were using our words differently. Once we get clear on our definitions, we can both agree that if we define dead as “no longer breathing and buried underground,” Alan Turring isn’t really “dead.”¹ **My central claim is that many psychological egoists make a similar, albeit much more subtle, mistake in their arguments for psychological egoism. **I’ll actually offer my argument for this claim in my next post. If you can’t jive with the distinction that I’ve drawn here between trivial and empirical truths, feel free to skip the next post. I won’t be defending that distinction and my argument relies on it. Notes: 1. I actually have no idea what happened to Alan Turing&amp;rsquo; body after he died.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A response to Your Comments on &#34;Why Paul Graham is (sort of) wrong about philosophy&#34;</title>
      <link>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/27/some-responses-to-your-comments-on-why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 23:18:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/27/some-responses-to-your-comments-on-why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;First, I want to thank you guys for reading, &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7801063&#34;&gt;criticizing, and commenting on&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/26/why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/&#34;&gt;my post&lt;/a&gt;. Given that there&amp;rsquo;s so many other excellent things you could have been reading, I&amp;rsquo;m honored that you spent a little time on what I&amp;rsquo;ve written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s respond to some comments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;credentials&#34;&gt;Credentials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of comments came up about my &amp;ldquo;credentials.&amp;rdquo; Here&amp;rsquo;s some info: I studied philosophy and religion as an undergrad at the University of Central Florida. After that, I went on to get my master&amp;rsquo;s degree in philosophy at Tufts University, a school with one of the top philosophy master&amp;rsquo;s programs in the country. None of this is supposed to make you think that I&amp;rsquo;m an authority on philosophy. I&amp;rsquo;m not. I know enough about philosophy to really appreciate how little I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-relationship-between-definitions-and-arguments&#34;&gt;The relationship between definitions and arguments&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of comments came up about the relationship between the meanings of words and philosophical questions. Here&amp;rsquo;s the passage that generated a lot of confusion:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Suppose I’m wondering whether it is it right for me demand extra equity because I’m the guy who came up with the idea for our startup. This is not a question about the meaning of my words. If someone responded to my wonderings by saying, “It depends what you mean by the word, ‘right’,” we’d probably think they have missed something.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s one comment that captures what a lot of people seemed to be worried about in my argument:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I haven&#39;t studied philosophy, so I may be naive here, but does this question NOT depend on the definition of &#34;right&#34;? In a practical discussion, maybe both parties would agree that &#34;right&#34; in this case means &#34;fair, in accordance with my contributions to this startup&#34;.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never meant to suggest that answers to philosophical questions do not depend on the meanings of key terms. In fact, I think its likely that any answer to any question we ask depends on the meaning of the terms we use to ask it. I should have been clearer on this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I was trying to suggest in above passage was that when we argue about what we ought to do, we are not arguing over the meaning of a word. The meaning of a word is usually settled by stipulation or by appealing to ordinary usage.¹ Neither stipulation, nor ordinary usage of the word &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; settles the question of whether, for example, it would be right for me to go on a killing spree tomorrow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To put the point in another way: Arguing about whether I should get extra equity as the idea guy is not like arguing over whether &amp;ldquo;a three sided figure&amp;rdquo; is a good definition of a triangle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe you disagree with me. That&amp;rsquo;s fine, but I think that ultimately this doesn&amp;rsquo;t help Graham&amp;rsquo;s position. I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why in the next section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;evidence-that-philosophers-could-pass-graham-s-placebo-test&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evidence that philosophers could pass Graham&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;placebo test&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of your comments raise philosophical questions. They are questions that philosophers have asked and are still asking.  So, it looks like we might be in a position to apply Graham&amp;rsquo;s placebo test to our own conversation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s ask ourselves: &amp;ldquo;Do we think we could tell the difference between the conversation we are having and a fake placebo conversation filled with nonsense?&amp;rdquo; I think we could, and if you disagree, this puts you in kind of awkward position, no? If you aren&amp;rsquo;t sure whether you could distinguish your own thoughts from nonsense, then maybe I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t take you seriously. If you think you can distinguish your comments and this conversation from nonsense, then, given that this a philosophical conversation, I think we have evidence that not all philosophical conversations are nonsensical. If we think that we could distinguish between a &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; philosophical conversation and nonsense, why shouldn&amp;rsquo;t we also think that many professors, who have studied philosophy a lot longer than we have, could also pass Graham&amp;rsquo;s placebo test?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, we can now see that if you disagree with my argument in the previous section (about the meaning of words) and if you think that you&amp;rsquo;re disagreement should be taken seriously, you are just helping to show that philosophy is not a trivial subject for stupid people. By the way, I don&amp;rsquo;t think you are crazy if you think that the meaning of the word &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; actually does settle our moral disputes. There are smart people who have thought this. They are called &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href=&#34;http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/naturalism-moral/&#34;&gt;analytical naturalists&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;did-i-misrepresent-graham-s-position&#34;&gt;Did I Misrepresent Graham&amp;rsquo;s position?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another passage that got me in to trouble:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;To say that a question can be answered by saying, “Depends on what you mean by X” is far from proving that the question is motivated by a confusion over words. Case in point: Did evolution happen? Depends on what you mean by “evolution.”&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;m not saying in this passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not saying that Graham thinks that all philosophical questions can be answered this way. In fact, as I point out a few sentences later, I&amp;rsquo;m not even really committed to saying that this is Graham&amp;rsquo;s argument for why philosophy is largely nonsense:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Maybe Graham wasn’t really trying to argue that philosophy is based on confusions over words...&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point in the above passage was just to say, &amp;ldquo;Where&amp;rsquo;s the argument that philosophy is nonsense? If Graham meant to argue for that by suggesting that you can answer a philosophical question with &amp;lsquo;Depends on what you mean by X,&amp;rsquo; then he should said more.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yikes. I&amp;rsquo;m out of words, so I guess that&amp;rsquo;s all the comments I&amp;rsquo;ll address for now. Thanks again for conversing with me on this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Obviously, whether this statement is true depends on what we mean when we use the word &amp;ldquo;meaning.&amp;rdquo; It turns out that this is a question that philosophers try to answer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Paul Graham is (sort of) Wrong About Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/26/why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 19:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/26/why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;A couple years ago, Paul Graham wrote &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.paulgraham.com/philosophy.html#f15n&#34;&gt;an essay about philosophy&lt;/a&gt;. The essay, on my reading, makes three central claims:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Philosophy has largely been driven by our failure to realize that our words are imprecise.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This failure is the result of failing to search for useful knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We can do philosophy better if we filter out thoughts that don’t meet a usefulness criterion.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I agree with a lot of what Graham says about philosophy in his essay, I think Graham is wrong on some of the more important points he makes. Before I say why I disagree with him, let me say that I think that Graham is a smart guy with a lot of interesting things to say and that I respect the dude a lot. We just happen to disagree on philosophy, and I, as a philosophical hacker, can’t resist expressing that disagreement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;are-we-really-just-confused-about-our-words&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we really just confused about our words?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s Graham:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;I would say that this has been, unfortunately for philosophy, the central fact of philosophy. Most philosophical debates are not merely afflicted by but driven by confusions over words. Do we have free will? Depends what you mean by &#34;free.&#34; Do abstract ideas exist? Depends what you mean by &#34;exist.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I sympathize the most with Graham’s first central claim, his claim that philosophy is largely driven by confusion over words. I have often wondered whether this sort of confusion was driving some of the discussion in my philosophy classes, but I have never worried that most of the questions I’ve discussed in my philosophical career are the result of tripping up over words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What bothered me most about Graham’s point is that he seems to be ignoring large branches of philosophy that are less plausibly charged with addressing questions that are “driven by confusions over words.” Graham mostly seems to discuss metaphysics in his essay, but there are (at least) two other branches of philosophy, ethics and epistemology, that he seems to ignore almost entirely. Its less plausible, moreover, that these two fields are driven by confusion over words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with ethics. Suppose I’m wondering &lt;a href=&#34;https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/24/should-the-idea-person-get-extra-equity/&#34;&gt;whether it is it right for me demand extra equity because I’m the guy who came up with the idea for our startup&lt;/a&gt;. This is not a question about the meaning of my words. If someone responded to my wonderings by saying, “It depends what you mean by the word, ‘right’,” we’d probably think they have missed something.¹ I don’t even think Graham would disagree with this. But why shouldn’t this count as evidence that there are a lot of philosophical questions that aren’t plagued by a confusion over words, especially given the fact that ethics has been a part of philosophy since before Aristotle’s &lt;em&gt;Metaphysics&lt;/em&gt; was written.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there’s epistemology, the study of knowledge. How do we know that we’re not in the matrix? How can we know anything if all our beliefs rest on beliefs that are unsupported by evidence? (We’ve got to have some “foundational beliefs.”)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, if someone responded to these questions by saying that we are confused about the meaning of the word “know,” we’d feel that they have missed the point.² When I ask, “How do I know I’m not in the matrix?,” I’m asking, “Why should I believe that I’m not in the matrix?” That question makes no reference to the word “know,” and yet it is still, in my opinion, an interesting question. Epistemology is another big branch in philosophy, so if we think that there are epistemological questions that aren’t driven by confusion over words, then we have to admit that there’s another large section of philosophical questions that aren’t misguided in the way that Graham suggests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, lets talk about metaphysics. Like I said, I’m more sympathetic to Graham’s point with respect to &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; kinds of metaphysics.³ Some metaphysical questions may be motivated by confusions over words and some metaphysical questions may be moral questions in disguise, but they are still important questions. Whether someone was “free to act” is something that we consider often in legal settings, and I think it’s right for us to ask this question before we lock someone up. If turns out that “I” don’t exist, to take another one of Graham’s examples, this might change the way we think about, for example, death.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if Graham and I are together in thinking that some metaphysical questions are confused, I don’t think the way that he argues for his point is very compelling. In fact, Graham doesn&amp;rsquo;t really seem to argue for this point at all. I think he comes closest to arguing for his point in the following passages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;Most philosophical debates are not merely afflicted by but driven by confusions over words. Do we have free will? Depends what you mean by &#34;free.&#34; Do abstract ideas exist? Depends what you mean by &#34;exist.&#34;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say that a question can be answered by saying, “Depends on what you mean by X” is far from proving that the question is motivated by a confusion over words. Case in point: Did evolution happen? Depends on what you mean by “evolution.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s another passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;There&#39;s no way to prove a text is meaningless. The closest you can get is to show that the official judges of some class of texts can&#39;t distinguish them from placebos.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This point seems more promising if I understand what’s being proposed. Graham seems to be saying that if a philosophy professor can’t distinguish a “real” philosophy paper from a fake, placebo paper that is purposely filled with nonsense, then the real paper is meaningless. If this is Graham’s proposal, I think that many philosophy professors could pass this test for many philosophical texts. There are definitely some charlatans posing as philosophers out there, but that doesn’t mean that all or most of philosophy is B.S.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe Paul wasn’t really trying to argue that philosophy is based on confusions over words. Maybe he was addressing his essay to people who already bought in to the idea that philosophy is a waste of time and who wanted to know how philosophers have managed to be so wrong for so long. If this is the intent of his essay, we should cut him some slack, but I’d be curious to know why he’s so sure that philosophers are just a sad, unintelligent bunch of people who got confused about their words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll address Graham’s other two points in subsequent posts. Maybe I’ll have that next post up by Thursday, but hopefully, Graham will pop in, make some comments, and I’ll have to delay that post until after him and I have talked a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=7801063&#34;&gt;the discussion on HackerNews&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/27/some-responses-to-your-comments-on-why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/&#34;&gt;my response&lt;/a&gt; to some of the comments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I take this to be one of the central points in G.E. Moore’s Principia Ethica.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is probably a controversial point. There are plenty of philosophers who are trying to analyze away skeptical worries by focusing on the meaning of the word “know.” Obviously, I think this is misguided, but I’m just a kid with a Master’s degree in philosophy, so what do I know.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though I’m suspicious of metaphysics, no one should take my suspicion very seriously.  I’ve only taken 1 metaphysics class, and I know people who could probably make me doubt whether I should harbor any suspicion towards metaphysics.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;In &lt;em&gt;Reasons and Persons&lt;/em&gt;, Derek Parfit argues that there are practical implications of ceasing to believe that the “I” exists.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m Glad my Dream Job Didn&#39;t work out</title>
      <link>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/22/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2014 03:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/22/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the past 5 years of my life, I&amp;rsquo;ve dreamed of having a job where I would get paid to think about interesting and important ideas and to try to get young people to be so passionate about those ideas that they would want to fight anyone who disagrees with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the past 5 years, I &lt;em&gt;hoped&lt;/em&gt; I was going to be a philosophy professor&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say &amp;ldquo;hoped&amp;rdquo; because I&amp;rsquo;ve always realized that philosophy professors have a sweet gig and a scandalous job description. I&amp;rsquo;ve always known that society was in the process of calling &amp;ldquo;BS&amp;rdquo; on anyone who wanted to make a living in the aforementioned way. The philosophy job market is terrible, and the humanities in general are having a rough time carving out some respect (and funding) in our STEM-focused society.¹&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope was that I could be one of the last ones to trick the powers at be into paying me for something that many of them didn&amp;rsquo;t really seem to care about (viz., teaching people to think critically). This past summer, however, my hopes were dashed. The world wasn&amp;rsquo;t cooperating with my dream, so I decided to give it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, that was a sad time, and I&amp;rsquo;ve only recently stopped worrying that giving up on my dreams has set me up for an incredibly awkward mid-life crisis. (I would probably start listening to metal again at 40 and drive across the country going to concerts with 20-somethings.) Now that I&amp;rsquo;ve stopped worrying, I&amp;rsquo;ve had a little time to reflect on my career path change, and perhaps surprisingly, I now think that this may have been a good thing. Here&amp;rsquo;s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world is a mess.² Lots of &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.dw.de/world-still-has-870-million-undernourished-people/a-17156507&#34;&gt;children starve&lt;/a&gt;, many &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/10/16/opinion/sex-trafficking-in-india.html?_r=0&#34;&gt;women are forced into sexual slavery&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=syrian+leader&amp;amp;oq=syrian+leader&amp;amp;aqs=chrome..69i57j0l5.2342j0j4&amp;amp;sourceid=chrome&amp;amp;espv=210&amp;amp;es_sm=93&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8#es_sm=93&amp;amp;espv=210&amp;amp;q=bashar+al-assad&amp;amp;tbm=nws&#34;&gt;some men persecute those who are powerless&lt;/a&gt;, which often &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wfp.org/crisis/syria&#34;&gt;causes more starving&lt;/a&gt; and more slavery. This is nothing new.³&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is new, however, is that I&amp;rsquo;m becoming so dissatisfied with the world as it is that I&amp;rsquo;ve &lt;em&gt;started&lt;/em&gt; to become willing to let the state of the world inform my career choices.&lt;sup&gt;4&lt;/sup&gt; I&amp;rsquo;ve started to ask, in other words, &amp;ldquo;In what career can I have the most positive impact on the world?&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup&gt;5&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And whenever I ask that question, it seems clear that if &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; became a philosophy professor,&lt;sup&gt;6&lt;/sup&gt;  I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t rank incredibly high on the I-make-the-world-more-awesome-via-my-career-meter.&lt;sup&gt;7&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if philosophy professor is out, what will I do? To be honest, I&amp;rsquo;m not 100% sure. I am, however, leaning heavily towards building a career as a mobile app developer. (I just got some internships as an Android Developer.) I also have some ideas for a tech startup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If neither of these career choices seem to be directly related to making the world better, that&amp;rsquo;s probably because they aren&amp;rsquo;t. I plan on making a positive impact via a more indirect route: make a lot of money and then donate so much of it that &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gatesfoundation.org/&#34;&gt;Bill and Melinda Gates&lt;/a&gt; will feel like a couple of Scrooges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its likely that the startup gig will fail, but that&amp;rsquo;s okay. I can still make a pretty penny (I think) if I really push this software development career. I know that this is not as sexy as a philosophy professor position, but I think I&amp;rsquo;m pretty happy with aspiring to be a kind of philosophical hacker/entrepreneur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I remember thinking to myself when I was deciding whether to pursue a career in the humanities that a materialistic society such as ours is going to have a hard time supporting or respecting a degree that does not cultivate the skills required to produce of a product.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps one of the best things about my philosophical education is that its given me eyes to see the all of the various ways in which the world could be improved.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;For some of my readers this may sound familiar. &lt;a href=&#34;http://kmattd.wordpress.com/2013/10/27/why-im-confused-about-my-upcoming-wedding/&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; the reason.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I ever would have been so dissatisfied with the world to leave philosophy on my own. I like it too much and I&amp;rsquo;m too self-interested to leave something so fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Kuddos to &lt;a href=&#34;http://80000hours.org/&#34;&gt;80,000 hours&lt;/a&gt; who, among many others, are partially responsible for this development.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;The conditional here is important. I&amp;rsquo;m not making the strong claim that philosophy professors in general don&amp;rsquo;t help the world that much. I&amp;rsquo;m only making the claim that if &lt;em&gt;I&lt;/em&gt; am serious about helping the world, I might be better off doing something else.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve also always thought it would be cool to be a pastor or to mentor young people. Unfortunately, if I&amp;rsquo;m interested in making the world as good as I can, I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ll have the privilege of working those jobs either.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>