<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Entrepreneurship on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/entrepreneurship/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Entrepreneurship on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 09:05:23 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://philosophicalhacker.com/tags/entrepreneurship/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>What I learned from my First Failed Startup</title>
      <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/post-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 09:05:23 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/post-title/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;For the past few months, I&amp;rsquo;ve been attending an incubator in downtown Orlando called &amp;ldquo;Starter Studio.&amp;rdquo; The original idea I pitched the incubator on was basically code school/code academy&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eric Reis talks about a balance between doing and thinking. I was too much about the doing. Brie tore my business apart in a few minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beware of capital intensive MVPs. Reference conversation with Gregg about amount of content to get beginners to job readiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have an audience or be prepared to build one (it will probably take years). Either way, be prepared to spend a lot of time doing S&amp;amp;M.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customer Interviews cannot be replaced by stats. Reference PG. Reference Chris encouraging me to interview consumers of blog content. Reference SS program encouraging me to do customer interviews.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You hear that you should target a niche, but how do you actually do this? How to actually target a niche. Chris taught me this (change site copy), along with a lunch and learn about specific landing pages with specific calls to action related to content you&amp;rsquo;re creating around a specific theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know 10 things you&amp;rsquo;ll do to promote whatever your building.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pick a flexible brand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, in a lot of cases, don&amp;rsquo;t buy a domain name before you have traction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because you think you&amp;rsquo;d use your product, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean that you&amp;rsquo;re building something great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each moment in business happens once. Reference Peter Thiel&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pay attention (to macro trends). Talk about conversation with Alex.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you quit your job, have potential co-founders in mind. If you have a really compelling idea, you should be able to get traction without quitting your job.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capital Intensive MVPs</title>
      <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/capital-intensive-mvps/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2016 08:21:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://philosophicalhacker.com/post/capital-intensive-mvps/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;According to Eric Reis, MVPs allow us to test our business&amp;rsquo; most important &amp;ldquo;hypotheses.&amp;rdquo; This is supposed to help us &amp;ldquo;fail faster,&amp;rdquo; but I&amp;rsquo;m finding that there are real differences in how much effort we have to put into our MVPs before we can validate our business hypotheses. In other words, some MVPs are more capital intensive than others. This is a big deal because you often can&amp;rsquo;t get favorable investment terms until you&amp;rsquo;ve shown that you&amp;rsquo;ve got product-market fit. You can&amp;rsquo;t do that without an MVP, and if you&amp;rsquo;re MVP is too difficult to build without capital, then you&amp;rsquo;re business will need exactly what it can&amp;rsquo;t have (under favorable terms): capital to create an MVP and validate its fundamental hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;expensive-solutions:39d2dcac40972781c1846ab6d4d8e099&#34;&gt;Expensive Solutions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking to customers before building anything is probably a great idea. Customer interviews probably yield tons of insight on how to build something people want. That said, I suspect that customer interviews aren&amp;rsquo;t enough. These interviews can give us great insight vis-a-vis the particular problems are customers are facing. They can also give us a clue as to what the solution to these problems should look like, but until we&amp;rsquo;ve got a prototyped solution &lt;em&gt;to sell them&lt;/em&gt;, we won&amp;rsquo;t know if we&amp;rsquo;ve actually created a solution that&amp;rsquo;s good enough for them to pay for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some MVPs are easier to build than others, and some MVPs are so difficult to build that its not feasible to build them without capital, capital that you can&amp;rsquo;t get (under favorable terms) because you haven&amp;rsquo;t shown that you&amp;rsquo;ve got product-market fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;high-customer-acquisition-costs:39d2dcac40972781c1846ab6d4d8e099&#34;&gt;High Customer Acquisition Costs&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you&amp;rsquo;ve built an MVP, you still have to be able to verify that people are willing to pay for your solution &lt;em&gt;at a price that&amp;rsquo;s high enough for you to offset the cost of acquiring those customers in the first place&lt;/em&gt;. The difficulty of verifying this varies from MVP to MVP, and customer acquisition costs can be prohibitive, even if we&amp;rsquo;re just trying to validate our business assumptions with an MVP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much easier for me to get my SnapChatGramBook app in front of 100 dousche-bag teenagers than it is to get my military simulator in front of 20 procurement folks at various defense companies. More generally, if you&amp;rsquo;ve got to charge a lot for your product, it&amp;rsquo;s going to take more money to get people to pay for it, and again, the costs may be prohibitive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion:39d2dcac40972781c1846ab6d4d8e099&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some ways, it feels like the lean startup movement has been a barrier to me realizing this. We&amp;rsquo;re taught that the &amp;ldquo;holy grail&amp;rdquo; of a startup&amp;rsquo;s journey is product-market fit and so we focus much of our thinking on finding that fit. I&amp;rsquo;m finding, however, that there really is important prior question to the question &amp;ldquo;Am I building something people want?&amp;rdquo; That question is &amp;ldquo;Do I have enough capital to find out whether I can build a viable business building something people want?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;ll Probably Try to Manipulate You</title>
      <link>http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2014 04:05:04 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/21/why-ill-probably-try-to-manipulate-you-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I became a hippie when I was a freshman in college. When I say I became a hippie, I don&amp;rsquo;t mean that I wore tie dye t-shirts all the time, smoked a lot of weed, and listened to &amp;ldquo;All you need is love&amp;rdquo; all day. I was a hippie even though I owned zero tie dye t-shirts, wasn&amp;rsquo;t cool enough to get invited to the weed parties, and had never heard that famous Beatles song that more conventional hippies love. Although I lacked the traditional trappings of a hippie, I became  hippie in a truer sense of the word:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was suspicious of &amp;ldquo;the system,&amp;rdquo; man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hippie readers know what &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo; is, but the rest of you will probably have to watch &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9GorqroigqM&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt;, a video that is more than a little responsible for my conversion experience. Since most of you will probably look at the 20 minute length time on that video and say, &amp;ldquo;yeah right. I&amp;rsquo;m not watching this,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;ll give you the readers digest version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are people with lots of money who are using morally questionable methods to retain and/or increase their profits. One of the morally questionable means by which &amp;ldquo;the system&amp;rdquo; keeps its profits rolling is to &lt;em&gt;manipulate&lt;/em&gt; consumers into purchasing products. The word &amp;ldquo;manipulate,&amp;rdquo; as I&amp;rsquo;m using it here, means to attempt to persuade someone in a way that circumvents their ability to make a rational decision about whether to engage in some behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s a &amp;ldquo;rational decision?&amp;rdquo; I don&amp;rsquo;t really know, but don&amp;rsquo;t get philosophical on me right now. Answering that question could take a lifetime for a philosopher like me, and we know enough about rational decisions to know that they aren&amp;rsquo;t motivated by ritual and the &lt;em&gt;manufactured&lt;/em&gt; emotional need to find satisfaction in the consumption of new products.¹&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that a rational purchase, for example, is not one that is made because we happened to see a commercial featuring a girl with shirt low-cut enough to convince us that having the product will make us more masculine. We know, to take another example, that a rational decision is not one that&amp;rsquo;s caused by a team of people working all day to find just the right combination of sugar, salt, fat, food additives, and visually appealing color-combinations to get you to buy another pack of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.google.com/search?q=publix+frosted+sugar+cookies&amp;amp;es_sm=91&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=MR98U-bLGYTJsQSfoIEI&amp;amp;ved=0CAkQ_AUoAg&amp;amp;biw=1277&amp;amp;bih=695&#34;&gt;those delicious Publix cookies with icing on them&lt;/a&gt;. (Those jokers have had me on the hook since high school.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we sometimes fall prey to manipulation by clever marketing. That’s not quite the point of the story here. Let’s get back to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just about a year after I became a hippie, something else happened: I became a wannabe philosophy professor. So, with my hippie and philosophy powers combined, I was on a mission to shape the minds of young people, to blow the whistle on &amp;ldquo;the system,&amp;rdquo; and to inoculate them against the B.S. that we are exposed to on a daily basis.²&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recently, the philosophy ship has sailed. I&amp;rsquo;m a wannabe hacker and entrepreneur now. I want to build a company that sells products, and, surprisingly, I’ve found that I’m willing to “trick” you into buying them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m joining “the system,” man.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why would a hippie-philosopher like me be willing to join “the system?” Well, it turns out that I’m also an abolitionist and a wannabe champion of the poor. I started &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.facebook.com/SAS.UCF&#34;&gt;a student group&lt;/a&gt; in undergrad that fought against human trafficking and I wrote &lt;a href=&#34;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0B-ddwOhnTTquMFUteVE5cUpKb3c/edit?usp=sharing&#34;&gt;my undergraduate thesis&lt;/a&gt; on our moral obligations to the world’s poor, and as I alluded to in my first post, I want to become the kind of person who has the desire and the &lt;em&gt;resources&lt;/em&gt; to make significant dents in the problems of human trafficking and global poverty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having resources means having money. Having money potentially means doing a tech startup. If I play the startup game well, I will pick an idea for a product that you will like and I will probably market the idea in ways that won’t appeal to your rational faculties. I will &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.helpscout.net/blog/psychology-of-color/&#34;&gt;pick colors that will make it more likely that you’ll like my product&lt;/a&gt;. I will write silly, emotionally appealing blog posts with silly justifications for why you need my product. I will try to find cool people that you look up to so that you’ll feel like you’re missing out on a cool thing if you don’t have I’m selling. In short, I will try to be manipulative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yikes. Writing those words out makes me feel crappier than I anticipated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Its strange, moreover, that a hippie-philosopher like me would wind up making morally grey decisions like this, but I honestly think that the moral trade off here is worth it: I treat you as a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Categorical_imperative#The_Second_Formulation&#34;&gt;“mere means”&lt;/a&gt; to the end of health and freedom for the world’s poor. Sorry, but &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.wfp.org/hunger/stats&#34;&gt;millions of children are dying&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, I’m open to being wrong about this. It might turn out that manipulative marketing techniques aren’t a key piece of pulling off a startup. It might also turn out that manipulating folk for the sake of the world’s poor is not worth the trade off. If I’m wrong, maybe I won’t try to manipulate you, but if I&amp;rsquo;m right, at least you can&amp;rsquo;t say I didn’t warn you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’m thinking here of the quotation Annie brings up from Victor Lebow who said, after realizing the productive capacity of our economy post WWII, “Our enormously productive economy demands that we make consumption our way of life, that we convert the buying and selling of goods into rituals, that we seek our spiritual satisfaction, our ego satisfaction in consumption&amp;hellip;”&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Real talk: I&amp;rsquo;m not going to lie and say that &lt;a href=&#34;https://philosophicalhacker.com/2014/04/21/why-im-glad-my-dream-job-didnt-work-out/&#34;&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t also just stoked about the idea of getting paid to talk and read about interesting, abstract issues that have much less to do with our well-being&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>