<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>management on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/tags/management/</link>
    <description>Recent content in management on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 09:18:03 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ya Better Recognize</title>
      <link>/post/ya-better-recognize/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 09:18:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/ya-better-recognize/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve picked up Psychologically Healthy Organizations from the APA to learn more about, among other things, the importance of recognition in the workplace. Here I want to share some highlights from the APA&amp;rsquo;s work on employee recognition in the workplace.
Recognition Meaningfully Shapes Performance The authors of Peopleware make some strong claims about team composition and the extent to which people can change in the workplace:
 For most efforts, success or failure is in the cards from the moment the team is formed and the initial directions set out&amp;hellip;managers are unlikely to change their people in any meaningful way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Humans</title>
      <link>/note/managing-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 17:30:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/note/managing-humans/</guid>
      <description>Michael Loop has worked as a manager at various companies in silicon valley, and his stories and lessons in Managing Humans are really helpful. Here are some miscellaneous takeaways from my recent reading.
Every Company (Probably) Has Big Problems Turns out I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen prey to the &amp;ldquo;grass is always greener&amp;rdquo; fallacy. I realize that no company is perfect, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always worked at companies that seem to have pretty big problems and I always imagine that there&amp;rsquo;s some company somewhere in Silicon Valley that &amp;mdash; while imperfect &amp;mdash; &amp;ldquo;has it&amp;rsquo;s shit together&amp;rdquo; on the fundamentals.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>