<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Management on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/management/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Management on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Ya Better Recognize</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/ya-better-recognize/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Nov 2017 09:18:03 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/ya-better-recognize/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve picked up &lt;em&gt;Psychologically Healthy Organizations&lt;/em&gt; from the APA to learn more about, among other things, the importance of recognition in the workplace. Here I want to share some highlights from the APA&amp;rsquo;s work on employee recognition in the workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recognition-meaningfully-shapes-performance&#34;&gt;Recognition Meaningfully Shapes Performance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The authors of &lt;em&gt;Peopleware&lt;/em&gt; make some strong claims about team composition and the extent to which people can change in the workplace:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most efforts, success or failure is in the cards from the moment the team is formed and the initial directions set out&amp;hellip;managers are unlikely to change their people in &lt;em&gt;any meaningful way.&lt;/em&gt;&amp;hellip;So the people who work for you through whatever period will be more or less the same at the end as they were at the beginning. If they’re not right for the job from the start, they never will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back on it, this is one of the more annoying passages of the book, as it makes an extremely strong claim with merely anecdotal evidence. The APA provides a nice, evidence-backed counter-point here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We know from extensive research that human behavior is shaped by its consequences and that providing positive consequences for employee performance is one of the most powerful ways to enhance performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is useful for me to keep in mind, as I&amp;rsquo;ve made the mistake in the past of believing that some folks are just &amp;ldquo;bad apples&amp;rdquo; when its more likely that there&amp;rsquo;s something problematic about the way in which they are being led or incentivized.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;recognition-done-right&#34;&gt;Recognition done right&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recognition done right has to be &lt;em&gt;timely&lt;/em&gt; and the form the recognition takes must be meaningful to the receiver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their claim that timeliness seems to rest on more general claims about human conditioning. Interestingly, one of the implications of timeliness is that: &amp;ldquo;saving up individual recognition for an annual performance appraisal or rewards banquet can be counterproductive.&amp;rdquo;&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One interesting idea they suggested that would likely increase timeliness of recognition is to rotate responsibility for who gives recognition at regular meetings. There&amp;rsquo;s a bit of a trade-off here, however, since this can hurt &amp;ldquo;contingency&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; people may feel like they have to give recognition even if there is nothing worth recognizing.&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a rel=&#34;footnote&#34; href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Timeliness and frequency of recognition may be sub-optimal in an organization because recognition itself may need to be reinforced for managers and employees. The chapter contains a section about convincing managers to recognize more and the authors say,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The trick lies in finding a catalyst&amp;ndash;an event or trigger mechanism that will help low-use managers personally experience recognition in a positive, meaningful way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible solution that jumped to my mind here is to recognize folks who do an exemplary job of recognizing others. A strong culture of recognition doesn&amp;rsquo;t come for free, so it makes sense that there may need to be some work to cultivate that culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One size doesn&amp;rsquo;t fit all when it comes to recognition. They had some interesting ideas for ensuring that recognition given is consistently valuable to the recipients within an organization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One idea is practiced at a company acquired by Bank of America. They have their managers ask employees on their first day to create a list of things that motivate them. Managers ended up with an &amp;ldquo;individualized motivation checklist for every employee.&amp;rdquo; In general, they seem to recommend involving employees in decisions about the form recognition takes since this increases &amp;ldquo;the employees&amp;rsquo; commitment and buy-in and the likelihood that what is done will be successful.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;footnotes&#34;&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:1&#34;&gt;Of course, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go to the other extreme and say something silly like what Simon Sinek says, &amp;ldquo;Its never the people. Its always the environment.&amp;rdquo; Again, very strong claim with merely anecdotal evidence. Probably, sometimes, its the people.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:2&#34;&gt;This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they are against annual rewards. Later on, they recommend a recognition plan that includes annual awards.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id=&#34;fn:3&#34;&gt;If peers are the ones responsible for doing the recognition, this could make timliness even better, since peers may have more time and visibility into reognition worthy behaviors, but this variant of the idea trades on the &amp;ldquo;significance of the provider&amp;rdquo; consideration since the recognizers here are peers, not someone with status in the organization.
 &lt;a class=&#34;footnote-return&#34; href=&#34;#fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[return]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Managing Humans</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/note/managing-humans/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2017 17:30:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/note/managing-humans/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Michael Loop has worked as a manager at various companies in silicon valley, and his stories and lessons in &lt;a href=&#34;http://managinghumans.com/&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Managing Humans&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; are really helpful. Here are some miscellaneous takeaways from my recent reading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;every-company-probably-has-big-problems&#34;&gt;Every Company (Probably) Has Big Problems&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out I&amp;rsquo;ve fallen prey to the &amp;ldquo;grass is always greener&amp;rdquo; fallacy. I realize that no company is perfect, but I&amp;rsquo;ve always worked at companies that seem to have pretty big problems and I always imagine that there&amp;rsquo;s some company somewhere in Silicon Valley that &amp;mdash; while imperfect &amp;mdash; &amp;ldquo;has it&amp;rsquo;s shit together&amp;rdquo; on the fundamentals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Loop actually worked at some pretty big companies in the Valley &amp;mdash; e.g., Slack, Palantir, Apple, and Netscape &amp;mdash; his experiences and commentary at a few points in &lt;em&gt;Managing Humans&lt;/em&gt; suggest otherwise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate meetings. Everyone hates them because we&amp;rsquo;ve all been to so many that have sucked unequivocally that we now walk into a conference room, sit down with our arms folded, and think, &amp;ldquo;OK, how long until this one is officially a waste of my time? How long until this one sucks?&amp;rdquo; And then it does. Time is wasted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out meetings are terrible everywhere. Somehow, even the folks in Silicon Valley haven&amp;rsquo;t figured out how to ensure that meetings don&amp;rsquo;t waste our time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[After a non-debatable mandate was given by the VP], as predicted, the team freaked&amp;hellip;We had a good solid week of organizational disarray and then we got back to work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turns out people everyone don&amp;rsquo;t like being told what to do, and that even the folks in Silicon Valley don&amp;rsquo;t trust their leadership enough to swallow a mandate without a week&amp;rsquo;s worth of &amp;ldquo;organizational disarray.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In high tech, we&amp;rsquo;re all in an incredible fucking hurry. We&amp;rsquo;re working against an unreasonable deadline and we&amp;rsquo;re over-committed on features. As a manager, your job is that of bullshit umbrella.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here he&amp;rsquo;s talking about how managers ought to shield their employees from the bullshit of managementese, a language that supposedly facilities communication across departments. My annotation on this comment at this point of the book was this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another example of how Loop presumed that there&amp;rsquo;s bullshit I&amp;rsquo;m the org. It&amp;rsquo;s the backdrop of this book in a lot of ways. Another title for the book could be &amp;ldquo;Managing Bullshit&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s another self-explanatory, shocking tale of political machinations in an organization:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe the execs won&amp;rsquo;t fire him because of the perception he has essential knowledge, but, I guarantee, those who are dependent on his black box of knowledge are concocting a devious plan to replace him and his knowledge because they want to grow . Right this second, three guys down the hall have rewritten Fez&amp;rsquo;s code in C and they&amp;rsquo;re secretly demonstrating their work to interested parties. They are building support, they are building a revolution, and they&amp;rsquo;re not going to stop until the person who is hindering their growth is gone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, this story didn&amp;rsquo;t happen &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; as its told, but Loop has based these stories on real life. So, at some the best companies I know about, execs are out of touch and team members are back stabbing each other. Amazing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my favorite. Loop explains an engineer&amp;rsquo;s risk factor for being outsourced by talking about company quality along two dimensions: process and product. He actually discusses 3 of the 4 possible states: lousy process / lousy product, lousy process / good product, good process / lousy product. The last possible state &amp;mdash; good process / good product &amp;mdash; he merely quips, &amp;ldquo;Wow. Where do you work?&amp;rdquo; Of course, this suggests that even the &amp;ldquo;great&amp;rdquo; companies in Silicon Valley often get either process or product wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;how-to-get-out-of-terrible-meetings&#34;&gt;How to Get out of Terrible Meetings&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a whole chapter on this. It was so refreshing to read someone being so candid about how much BS is typically involved with meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The basic strategy he outlines is to identify what type of meeting you&amp;rsquo;re in and then to just give &amp;ldquo;the players&amp;rdquo; what they want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;informational meetings,&amp;rdquo; the players are listeners and the talkers. Talkers just want to convey information. This means that you need to tell people who are trying to debate the issue to schedule a follow up and make sure they don&amp;rsquo;t invite you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;conflict resolution meetings,&amp;rdquo; there are &amp;ldquo;pros&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;cons.&amp;rdquo; Pros are getting what they want. Cons are getting screwed. Getting out of this meeting requires that someone communicate a set of concrete steps to help the cons feel less screwed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t think this taxonomy meetings and accompanying exit strategies are exhaustive, but they&amp;rsquo;re a great start.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-i-m-occasionally-cranky-at-work&#34;&gt;Why I&amp;rsquo;m Occasionally Cranky at Work&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In &amp;ldquo;Incrementalists and Completionists,&amp;rdquo; Loop divies folks up into two camps. &amp;ldquo;Completionists&amp;rdquo; have vision and they have strong opinions about how to solve a problem &amp;ldquo;The Right Way&amp;trade;.&amp;rdquo; They are big on solving the problem completely. Incrementalists, as their name implies, are more about hacks and gerry-rigs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loop does a great job about going over the pros and cons of type, which was great for me to read because &amp;mdash; for better or worse &amp;mdash; I&amp;rsquo;m a &amp;ldquo;completionist&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;incrementalists&amp;rdquo; often annoy me. That wasn&amp;rsquo;t the best part about the chapter though. The best part for me was this passage:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With all of their strategic vision, &amp;ldquo;completionists&amp;rdquo; often lack common corporate and people sense. Yes, they have a five-year technical roadmap in their heads, but they have nary a clue how to start pushing that agenda with the 12 different people who need to get on board to make anything happen. This is why &amp;ldquo;completionists&amp;rdquo; often get incorrectly labeled as curmudgeons. Sure, they&amp;rsquo;re cranky, but it&amp;rsquo;s not cranky for crankiness&amp;rsquo;s sake, it&amp;rsquo;s because they don&amp;rsquo;t have the communication and people skills to convince the company of the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read that and thought, &amp;ldquo;Wow. That&amp;rsquo;s me.&amp;rdquo; Most of the time, thinking about how to manage people is scary and complicated for me, so I often prefer to stick to managing bits. It turns out that for &amp;ldquo;completionists&amp;rdquo; like me, this is a recipe for crankiness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loop&amp;rsquo;s book helped me adjust my expectations about working in software companies a little bit. Less pretentiously, the book helped me grow up a little. I recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>