<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Business on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/business/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Business on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 22:11:45 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/business/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Some problems with the impossibility of achieving OKRs</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/okr-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 22:11:45 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/okr-problems/</guid>
      <description>In many ways, OKRs are a neat way of structuring goals for a company. According to Marty Cagan, product managers should be especially interested in OKRs as a goal setting framework since they are a better way of tracking product work than a &amp;ldquo;product roadmap.&amp;rdquo; I agree with Cagan. OKRs are often better than typical product road maps.
However, there’s an aspect of OKRs that I think is morally and psychologically problematic: the idea that OKRs should be impossible to entirely achieve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Business and the Cartesian Demon: How not to Study Business</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/business-and-cartesian-demon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 21:02:19 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/business-and-cartesian-demon/</guid>
      <description>A few hundred years ago, Renè Descartes, the fella who brought us the Cartesian coordinate system 📉, isolated himself for a while to figure out (among other things) whether we can know anything for certain. The result of his retreat was his Meditations on First Philosophy, one of the most important philosophical texts of the modern era and one of my personal favorites.
Early on in his Meditations, he decides that it&amp;rsquo;d be useful to engage in a thought experiment.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>