<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>On Philosophy on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/categories/On-Philosophy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in On Philosophy on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 23:18:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/categories/On-Philosophy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A response to Your Comments on &#34;Why Paul Graham is (sort of) wrong about philosophy&#34;</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/27/some-responses-to-your-comments-on-why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 May 2014 23:18:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/27/some-responses-to-your-comments-on-why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>First, I want to thank you guys for reading, criticizing, and commenting on my post. Given that there&amp;rsquo;s so many other excellent things you could have been reading, I&amp;rsquo;m honored that you spent a little time on what I&amp;rsquo;ve written.
Now, let&amp;rsquo;s respond to some comments:
Credentials A couple of comments came up about my &amp;ldquo;credentials.&amp;rdquo; Here&amp;rsquo;s some info: I studied philosophy and religion as an undergrad at the University of Central Florida.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why Paul Graham is (sort of) Wrong About Philosophy</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/26/why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 May 2014 19:06:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/2014/05/26/why-paul-graham-is-sort-of-wrong-about-philosophy/</guid>
      <description>A couple years ago, Paul Graham wrote an essay about philosophy. The essay, on my reading, makes three central claims:
 Philosophy has largely been driven by our failure to realize that our words are imprecise.
 This failure is the result of failing to search for useful knowledge.
 We can do philosophy better if we filter out thoughts that don’t meet a usefulness criterion.
  While I agree with a lot of what Graham says about philosophy in his essay, I think Graham is wrong on some of the more important points he makes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>