<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>statistics on Philosophical Hacker</title>
    <link>/tags/statistics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in statistics on Philosophical Hacker</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/tags/statistics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Traffic Fatalities by Vehicle Weight and Size with Tidyverse</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/analyzing-traffic-fatalities-by-vehicle-weight-and-size/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/analyzing-traffic-fatalities-by-vehicle-weight-and-size/</guid>
      <description>I bought a car recently. I’m cheap and practical and I’m going to be a father soon, so the only things I really cared about were:
 will the car keep my wife and child safe if they’re in an accident will the car keep running reliably how do I get 👆 those two things on the cheap  I’ve also been getting into machine learning and data science recently, so I thought it’d be useful to answer them using some data science tools.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should we refactor files we&#39;re working on?</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/are-source-file-diffs-serially-correlated/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 13:14:58 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/post/are-source-file-diffs-serially-correlated/</guid>
      <description>When programming, always follow the camping rule: Always leave the code base healthier than when you found it.
&amp;mdash; Martin Fowler, Refactoring
   The Boy Scouts of America have a simple rule that we can apply to our profession. Leave the campground cleaner than you found it.
&amp;mdash; Robert Martin, Clean Code
 Many of us share the attitude expressed by the above Fowler and Martin quotes. The attitude presumes that code we&amp;rsquo;re working on now will change again soon, and we&amp;rsquo;ll reap the benefits of a refactor when that happens.</description>
      
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why PMs Should Study Statistics: An Interactive Essay</title>
      <link>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/why-pms-should-study-statistics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2019 08:22:51 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.philosophicalhacker.com/why-pms-should-study-statistics/</guid>
      <description>Marty Cagan &amp;ndash; seasoned product manager and author of a book and blog that makes practically every recommended reading list for new product managers &amp;ndash; says that there are two academic courses that “every product manager should take”: finance and computer science. In this interactive essay, I suggest we add another course to this list: statistics. A strong understanding of statistics facilitates three key responsibilities of product managment: understanding analytics, implementing cooprorate change, and making accurate forecasts.</description>
      
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
